TST4-MUC4-0005

CLANDESTINE, 26 AUG 88 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] AMINTA PLATERO WAS KILLED WHEN HER CAR WAS HIT BY ANOTHER CAR DRIVEN BY FORMER DEPUTY PUBLIC SECURITY MINISTER RINALDO GOLCHER. AT THE TIME OF THE ACCIDENT, GOLCHER WAS ACCOMPANIED BY U.S. MILITARY ATTACHE ANGEL MENENDEZ. THE INCIDENT OCCURRED AT 0100 ON 26 AUGUST AT THE INTERSECTION OF WEST 1ST STREET AND NORTH 51ST AVENUE. COL GOLCHER WAS SUPPOSEDLY IN ISRAEL WHERE HE WAS SENT AS THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT'S MILITARY ATTACHE; HOWEVER, THE WELL-KNOWN LEADER OF THE DEATH SQUADS WAS SEEN AT 0100 IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR ACCOMPANIED BY NONE OTHER THAN THE U.S. MILITARY REPRESENTATIVE IN OUR COUNTRY. THIS HAPPENED ONLY HOURS AFTER COLONEL [ADOLFO ARNOLDO] MAJANO'S BODYGUARDS WERE MURDERED.

THE CIRCUMSTANCES SURROUNDING THIS INCIDENT RAISE SEVERAL QUESTIONS. WHAT WERE THESE TWO SOLDIERS DOING AT 0100? WHERE WERE GOLCHER'S BODYGUARDS? WHERE WERE HIS COMPANION'S BODYGUARDS? THE TWO MEN WERE PROBABLY RETURNING FROM A CORRUPTION CENTER, A NIGHT CLUB--ONE OF THOSE EXCLUSIVE CLUBS WHERE THE U.S. ADVISERS AND OTHER U.S. AND SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS SPEND THE DOLLARS THEY STEAL FROM THE FUNDS ALLOTTED TO EL SALVADOR AND WHERE THEY PLAN CRIMES AGAINST THE PEOPLE.

MUCH MORE COULD BE SAID; HOWEVER, THE TRUTH IS THAT THE INCIDENT WAS NO MERE ACCIDENT. MRS PLATERO IS ANOTHER VICTIM OF THE MADNESS AFFECTING AN ARMY DIRECTED BY U.S. ADVISERS. THERE IS NOT MUCH DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THIS INCIDENT AND THE HURLING OF A GRENADE BY A SOLDIER DRIVEN CRAZY BY THE PSYCHOLOGICAL TERRORISM PRACTICED BY THE ARMY ADVISERS AND CHIEFS. THERE IS NO DOUBT IN OUR MINDS THAT GOLCHER WILL NOT BE TRIED FOR THIS NEW CRIME, JUST AS HE HAS NOT BEEN TRIED FOR THE MANY CRIMES HE HAS BEEN RESPONSIBLE FOR AS CHIEF OF THE REPRESSIVE CORPS AND DEATH SQUADS.

TST4-MUC4-0011

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 9 AUG 88 (LA PRENSA) -- [LETTER SENT BY PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS TO NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA] [TEXT] DEAR MR PRESIDENT:

ON THE ROAD TOWARD ACHIEVING PEACE, WE HAVE OFTEN EXPERIENCED SETBACKS AND DIFFICULT TIMES. POWERFUL FORCES ARE TRYING TO JUSTIFY VIOLENCE AND WAR EVERY TIME DIPLOMATIC CHANNELS OR COMMITMENTS ARE NOT FOLLOWED OR MET.

WHEN THERE IS AN ARMED STRUGGLE AND WHEN THOUSANDS ARE KILLED ON THE BATTLEFIELD, THOSE WHO PROMOTE VIOLENCE NEVER CONCLUDE FROM THOSE USELESS KILLINGS THAT WAR IS FUTILE. THEY DO NOT BELIEVE THAT PEACE CAN BE ACHIEVED THROUGH DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION.

IT WILL ALWAYS BE EASIER TO RECTIFY MISTAKES WHEN THE WEAKNESSES ARE POLITICAL OR WHEN ERRORS ARE MADE ON THE ROAD TO PEACE. WE CANNOT BRING THE DEAD BACK TO LIFE, AND VIOLENCE BORN OF HATRED TAKES A LONG TIME TO HEAL.

I BELIEVE, MR PRESIDENT, THAT IT WOULD BE ENCOURAGING IF YOU WERE TO RECTIFY SOME POLITICAL DECISIONS YOUR GOVERNMENT MADE FOLLOWING THE UNFORTUNATE INCIDENTS AT NANDAIME. IT IS IMPORTANT TO REOPEN THE COMMUNICATIONS MEDIA THAT ARE CLOSED. IT IS NECESSARY TO RELEASE THE PRISONERS AND TO REVOKE THE SENTENCES IMPOSED UPON THEM AS PUNISHMENT FOR INVOLVEMENT IN THOSE INCIDENTS. THE PEACE PLAN TO WHICH WE ARE COMMITTED OBLIGES US TO RESTORE CONFIDENCE AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. OUR MOST SACRED COMMITMENT IS TO CONTINUE PROGRESSING ON THE PATH TOWARD DEMOCRATIZATION.

IT IS IMPERATIVE THAT YOUR GOVERNMENT AND THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS RESUME NEGOTIATIONS TO SECURE A PERMANENT END TO MILITARY ACTIONS IN NICARAGUA. THIS COULD VERY WELL BE AN ENCOURAGING EXAMPLE FOR MANY CENTRAL AMERICAN AND OTHER COUNTRIES. I OFFER YOU OUR COSTA RICAN TERRITORY FOR THE RESUMPTION OF SUCH NEGOTIATIONS. I ALSO OFFER YOU ALL THE ASSISTANCE WITHIN MY MEANS TO ENABLE SUCH NEGOTIATIONS TO TAKE PLACE.

I UNDERSTAND THAT YOU WILL ATTEND THE UPCOMING INAUGURAL CEREMONY IN ECUADOR. I BELIEVE IT WOULD BE A SIGN OF CONFIDENCE IN THE FUTURE OF PEACE, A NOBLE GESTURE TOWARD RODRIGO BORJA, AND WOULD AID IN STRENGTHENING THE ECUADORAN DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IF YOU ATTENDED THE CEREMONY IN QUITO AFTER REVERSING THE SETBACKS INCURRED AS A RESULT OF ANTIDEMOCRATIC ACTIONS, SUCH AS PENALIZING THE COMMUNICATIONS MEDIA AND DEPRIVING MEN AND WOMEN OF THEIR LIBERTY.

ONLY IF WE HAVE THE STRENGTH TO CORRECT OUR MISTAKES AND THE VISION TO CONTINUE ON THE PATH OUTLINED IN THE PEACE PLAN CAN CENTRAL AMERICANS PREVENT THE CONTINUANCE OF THE ARMED AGGRESSION AGAINST OUR PEOPLES. A LATIN AMERICAN COMMITMENT TO PEACE ALSO REQUIRES EFFORTS TO ACHIEVE INDEPENDENCE AND DEMOCRACY. WE WILL NOT BE GRANTED ANOTHER POLITICAL OPPORTUNITY TO FORGE HISTORY. IT IS UNLIKELY THAT THERE WILL BE A NEW OPPORTUNITY FOR RECONCILIATION TO ALLOW TODAY'S YOUTH A DIFFERENT FUTURE, A NEW OPPORTUNITY TO PUT ASIDE THEIR WEAPONS AND TO WORK FOR A BETTER FUTURE.

TST4-MUC4-0017

SAN SALVADOR, 17 SEP 88 (DIARIO LATINO) -- [TEXT] IN RECENT MILITARY OPERATIONS, ARMED FORCES UNITS KILLED ONE REBEL, SEIZED 45,000 CARTRIDGES AND OTHER WAR MATERIEL, AND DESTROYED AN UNDERGROUND HIDEOUT.

THE TERRORIST DIED IN A CLASH WITH 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE UNITS. THE SOLDIERS HAD DETECTED AN FMLN COLUMN DEPLOYING NEAR LA ARANA HILL IN ESTANZUELAS, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT.

THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE ALSO REPORTED THAT LIBERTAD BATTALION TROOPS FOUND AN UNDERGROUND WAREHOUSE NEAR THE EL CASTANO FARM IN NEJAPA, NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR. IN THE WAREHOUSE, THE BRIGADE UNITS FOUND 45,000 CARTRIDGES OF VARIOUS CALIBERS AND A LARGE AMOUNT OF MATERIAL FOR MANUFACTURING EXPLOSIVES.

IN ADDITION, ATLACATL BATTALION COUNTERINSURGENCY UNITS RECENTLY SEIZED 15 FRAGMENTATION GRENADES, 5 CLAYMORE MINES, 5 BOOBY TRAPS, 10 UNITS OF TNT, LOADED CARTRIDGE CLIPS, AND 7 KNAPSACKS CONTAINING CIVILIAN CLOTHING, OLIVE-GREEN UNIFORMS, AND COMMUNIST PROPAGANDA. THESE ITEMS WERE APPARENTLY LEFT BEHIND BY WOUNDED REBELS WHO MANAGED TO FLEE AFTER A CLASH WITH THE BATTALION MEMBERS AT THE FOOT OF EL CHINO HILL IN SAN FRANCISCO MORAZAN, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT.

FURTHERMORE, 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE UNITS PATROLLING THE ZONE OF EL RODEO IN EL CONGO, SANTA ANA DEPARTMENT, DISCOVERED A 200-METER UNDERGROUND HIDEOUT BIG ENOUGH TO CONCEAL AT LEAST 250 INSURGENTS. THE BRIGADE UNITS PROCEEDED TO DESTROY THE HIDEOUT.

TST4-MUC4-0020

SANTIAGO, 22 SEP 88 (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [EXCERPTS] THE CHILEAN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMITTEE HAS HANDED GENERAL PINOCHET A PUBLIC PETITION REQUESTING HIM TO EXPLAIN TO THE COUNTRY SOME SERIOUS CRIMES, WHICH CANNOT BE DENIED, THAT OCCURRED DURING HIS TERM IN OFFICE. THIS PETITION EXPRESSES THE CONCERN OF THE CHILEAN PEOPLE REGARDING THESE CRIMES.

THE PETITION WAS RELEASED BY REPRESENTATIVES OF THE CHILEAN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMITTEE, WHICH IS HEADED BY LAWYER JAIME CASTILLO VELASCO AND MAXIMO PACHECO, WHO WAS EDUCATION MINISTER DURING PRESIDENT EDUARDO FREI'S ADMINISTRATION.

THE PETITION, WHICH IS ADDRESSED TO MR AUGUSTO PINOCHET UGARTE--APPOINTED PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC FOR ANOTHER PERIOD OF GOVERNMENT [AS HEARD] AND THE HIGHEST EXECUTIVE BRANCH REPRESENTATIVE FOR THE PAST 15 YEARS--POINTS OUT SOME SERIOUS HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS, WHICH MUST BE EXPLAINED.

THESE VIOLATIONS OCCURRED DURING THE PERIOD FOLLOWING 11 SEPTEMBER 1973, WHEN NATIONAL LIFE BECAME UNCONTROLLABLE, SEVERAL HOMES WERE RAIDED, AND MANY PEOPLE WERE HARASSED AND KILLED. THE PETITION ALSO REQUESTS CLARIFICATION ON CASES OF PEOPLE WHO INEXPLICABLY HAVE BEEN MISSING SINCE THEIR ARREST FOR REASONS STILL UNKNOWN. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THROUGH ITS CHILDREN AND ADOLESCENTS' DEPARTMENT, THE CHILEAN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMITTEE HAS EXPLAINED ITS CONCERN OVER THE USE OF CHILDREN IN PROPAGANDA SPOTS SUPPORTING THE YES-VOTE, WHICH ARE BROADCAST ON TELEVISION. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THE COMMUNIQUE RELEASED BY THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMITTEE ENDS BY URGING THE ADVERTISEMENT PROFESSIONALS WHO CREATED THIS TYPE OF PROPAGANDA TO BE MORE CREATIVE AND POSITIVE INSTEAD OF ADDING HORROR TO THE PAIN OF THE CHILEAN NATION.

TST4-MUC4-0021

BOGOTA, 22 SEP 88 (EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK) -- [TEXT] THREE NEW TERRORIST ATTACKS WERE CARRIED OUT EARLY THIS MORNING, AT AN AIRPORT IN BARRANQUILLA, AT THE COMMUNIST PARTY HEADQUARTERS IN FLORENCIA, AND AT THE CERRO AZUL MILITARY INSTALLATIONS IN URABA. THE POLICE CONFIRMED THAT UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS ARMED WITH MACHINEGUNS ATTACKED THE COLOMBIAN AIR FORCE INSTALLATIONS IN THE CAPITAL OF ATLANTICO. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES.

THE MALAMBO AREA, CLOSE TO THE BARRANQUILLA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT, WHERE THE AIR BASE IS LOCATED, WAS IMMEDIATELY MILITARIZED. GUARDS AT THE SITE REPELLED THE ATTACK, WHICH WAS APPARENTLY STAGED BY GUERRILLAS.

SIMILARLY, IT WAS LEARNED THAT A BOMB EXPLODED TODAY AT THE COMMUNIST PARTY HEADQUARTERS IN THE CAPITAL OF CAQUETA, CAUSING CONSIDERABLE PROPERTY DAMAGE. IT WAS IMMEDIATELY ANNOUNCED THAT NO ONE HAD BEEN INJURED OR KILLED IN THE EXTREMIST ACTION.

IT WAS ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT SUSPECTED SUBVERSIVES STAGED ANOTHER ATTACK ON THE INSTALLATIONS OF THE BATTALION STATIONED IN URABA AT CERRO AZUL, NEAR TURBO.

THESE TERRORIST ATTACKS TOOK PLACE 1 DAY AFTER THE SERIOUS ATTACK LAUNCHED AT THE 2D ARMY DIVISION HEADQUARTERS IN BUCARAMANGA, WHICH RESULTED IN SEVEN PEOPLE INJURED AND CONSIDERABLE PROPERTY DAMAGE, AFFECTING NINE HOMES.

TST4-MUC4-0023

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 26 SEP 88 (TELEVISORA NATIONAL) -- [REPORT ON NEWS CONFERENCE HELD BY ATTORNEY GENERAL CARLOS VILLALAZ, ASSISTANT ATTORNEY GENERAL MARIO BALLESTEROS, PANAMA DEFENSE FORCES (FDP) G-2 LIEUTENANT COLONEL GUILLERMO WONG, AND NATIONAL INVESTIGATIONS DEPARTMENT (DENI) DIRECTOR LIEUTENANT COLONEL NIVALDO MADRINAN WITH LOCAL AND INTERNATIONAL REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [BEGIN RECORDING] [MADRINAN] THE PLAN INCLUDED SEVERAL POINTS. THE PURPOSE OF THIS PLAN WAS TO PRESSURE GENERAL NORIEGA TO RESIGN FROM HIS MILITARY POST IN LATE AUGUST.

THE PSYCHOLOGICAL OBJECTIVES OF THIS PLAN WERE: TO INTENSIFY AND SPREAD THE REPUDIATION OF NORIEGA WITHIN THE FDP; TO INTENSIFY AND SPREAD THE REPUDIATION OF NORIEGA'S COLLABORATORS BY MENTIONING SPECIFIC NAMES; TO CONVINCE NORIEGA THAT HE HAD LOST FDP SUPPORT AND THAT HIS REGIME WAS UNSUSTAINABLE; TO CONVINCE NORIEGA'S PANAMANIAN COLLABORATORS THAT HE HAD LOST FDP SUPPORT AND THAT HIS REGIME WAS UNSUSTAINABLE; TO CONVINCE FOREIGN GOVERNMENTS AND NORIEGA ALLIES, PARTICULARLY CUBA AND NICARAGUA, THAT HE HAD LOST FDP SUPPORT AND THAT HIS GOVERNMENT WAS UNSUSTAINABLE; TO CONVINCE GOVERNMENTS THAT WERE HOSTILE TO NORIEGA, ESPECIALLY VENEZUELA AND COLOMBIA, THAT HE HAD LOST FDP SUPPORT AND THAT HIS REGIME WAS UNSUSTAINABLE; TO CONVINCE FOREIGN REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENTS THAT DEALT WITH NORIEGA, SUCH AS THE FMLN AND THE M-19, THAT HE HAD LOST FDP SUPPORT AND THAT HIS REGIME WAS UNSUSTAINABLE; AND TO MOVE THE ANTI-NORIEGA SECTOR WITHIN THE FDP TO SUPPORT SPECIFIC ACTIONS AGAINST NORIEGA'S REGIME.

THE FDP MEMBERS, OFFICERS, AND TROOPS WERE THE TARGETS OF THIS PLAN. WE SEE HOW SOME WERE TAKEN IN BY THE PSYCHOLOGICAL OPERATIONS PLAN. THE TARGETS OF THIS PLAN WERE GEN NORIEGA, NORIEGA'S PANAMANIAN COLLABORATORS WITHIN THE FDP, SOME CIVILIANS, FOREIGN GOVERNMENTS THAT ARE NORIEGA'S ALLIES, FOREIGN GOVERNMENTS THAT ARE HOSTILE TO NORIEGA, AND FOREIGN REVOLUTIONARY ORGANIZATIONS THAT DEAL WITH NORIEGA. THEY IDENTIFIED ALL OF NORIEGA'S VULNERABILITIES, AS WELL AS THE VULNERABILITIES OF ALL THE TARGETS WE HAVE ALREADY MENTIONED.

THERE WERE CERTAIN THEMES USED IN THESE PSYCHOLOGICAL OPERATIONS, AND THE MEDIA FELL FOR THEM MANY TIMES. THIS IS WHY WE REPEATEDLY ASKED THEM NOT TO FALL FOR THIS MISINFORMATION.

THESE THEMES INCLUDED: BY IMPOSING HIS ARBITRARY NATURE AND CORRUPTION, NORIEGA IS PERVERTING THE FDP AND PROMOTING THE DISINTEGRATION OF THAT MILITARY INSTITUTION. THE FDP HAVE BECOME A MAFIA THAT IS HEADING TOWARD DISGRACE. THIS IS A TOPIC THAT HAS BEEN DISCUSSED IN LEAFLETS AND MANY PUBLICATIONS.

BY DISRUPTING THE CONSTITUTIONAL ORDER AT HIS WHIM, NORIEGA IS PROVOKING A PROFOUND SOCIAL, ECONOMIC, AND POLITICAL CRISIS THAT IS RUINING THE COUNTRY. THIS IS DONE TO HIDE THOSE WHO ARE TRULY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CRISIS WE ARE EXPERIENCING. THE LONGER NORIEGA REMAINS IN POWER, THE MORE PROBABLE BECOMES A U.S., CUBAN, OR SOVIET INTERVENTION. THE DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL CONFLICTS PROVOKED BY NORIEGA NEGATIVELY AFFECT THE PERSONAL WELL-BEING OF THE FDP MEMBERS AND THEIR FAMILIES.

NORIEGA'S FALL IS INEVITABLE AND THE FDP SHOULD NOT FALL WITH HIM. TO SAVE THE FDP AND THE REPUBLIC OF PANAMA, THE FDP MUST REMOVE NORIEGA FROM OFFICE. THIS IS WHY THERE WERE SIREN SONGS THAT AN INTERNAL COUP WAS UNDER WAY.

THE STATE SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS HAVE BEEN FOLLOWING THIS CASE FOR 5 MONTHS AND WE KNOW THE FUGITIVES ARE IN THE UNITED STATES. WE KNOW WHERE THEY LEFT FROM. NO ONE CAN DENY THE ASSOCIATION OF CERTAIN U.S. CITIZENS WHO ARE INVOLVED IN THIS OPERATION WITH THE PANAMANIAN GROUPS THAT WERE CAPTURED.

WE HAVE THE EVIDENCE, THE WEAPONS, THE INSTRUMENTS USED FOR MISINFORMATION, THE PLANS, AND THE MAPS WITH THE TARGETS FOR VIOLENCE. IMPORTANT PEOPLE WHO WERE GOING TO BE KIDNAPPED HAD ALSO BEEN MARKED ON THESE MAPS. THEY HAD MARKED THE BRIDGES THAT WERE TO BE DESTROYED.

GENTLEMEN, WE KNOW THE POWER OF WEAPONS AND WE KNOW HOW TO USE THEM. WE KNOW THE DAMAGE THEY CAN DO. THEREFORE, BEFORE THERE WAS A VIOLENT CONFRONTATION BETWEEN THE PANAMANIAN PEOPLE AND THEIR FDP, WE WENT ONE STEP AHEAD OF THEIR PLANS. IF ARRESTS WERE MADE, IT WAS BECAUSE WE WANTED TO AVOID A CONFRONTATION WITH INEXPERIENCED GROUPS THAT ALLOWED THEMSELVES TO BE USED FOR THE PERSONAL BENEFIT OF THOSE WHO RECEIVED, WITH A SIREN SONG, THE PROMISE OF THE PANAMANIAN PEOPLE'S $30 MILLION THAT ERIC ARTURO DELVALLE WAS GOING TO USE FOR SUBVERSIVE ACTS, BLOODY ACTS TO BATHE OUR PEOPLE IN BLOOD, AS IN THE CASE OF THE STRUGGLE OF OUR BROTHER COUNTRIES IN LATIN AND CENTRAL AMERICA.

WE WILL NOT PERMIT THAT. THAT IS WHY WE DECIDED TO GO ONE STEP AHEAD AND FOIL THESE PLANS THAT HAVE A CERTAIN PURPOSE AND THAT WOULD RESULT IN MOURNING AND PAIN FOR PANAMANIAN FAMILIES.

WE HAVE THE EVIDENCE AND THOSE WHO WERE ARRESTED WERE DAMN WELL ARRESTED: ALBERTO CONTE, FRED BOYD, AND ALL THOSE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN WORKING BEHIND THE SCENES SO EDUARDO HERRERA AND FRIENDS CAN LIVE LIKE KINGS IN THE UNITED STATETS, SO THEY CAN LIVE THEIR LIVES DRINKING CHAMPAGNE AND EATING PHEASANT.

EDUARDO HERRERA WAS DISMISSED FROM A DIPLOMATIC POST FOR SMUGGLING 40 BOXES OF WHISKEY PER WEEK INTO ISRAEL. HE IS THE KIND OF PERSON PROTECTED BY THE PENTAGON AND ELLIOTT ABRAMS. HE IS ELLIOTT ABRAMS' HERO.

THERESA WELLINGTON OF THE [U.S.] EMBASSY IN MEXICO, WHO GAVE THESE PEOPLE--WHO LEFT PANAMA FOR MEXICO-- THEIR VISAS IN 10 MINUTES BY ABRAMS' ORDERS, HAS ALSO BECOME ONE OF OUR PEOPLE'S ENEMIES. [END RECORDING] [CONTINUED]

TST4-MUC4-0024

SANTIAGO, 28 SEP 88 (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [EXCERPT] THIS MORNING AT APPROXIMATELY 0630 THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC] HEADQUARTERS IN THE CITY OF ARICA WAS ATTACKED. THE PDC'S PREMISES ARE LOCATED AT 683 SOTOMAYOR STREET, IN THE DOWNTOWN AREA OF THE CITY. THE IDENTITY OF THE ATTACKERS IS UNKNOWN.

THE REPORT WAS FILED BY FORMER CONGRESSMAN HUMBERTO BALZA, THE PRESIDENT OF THE PDC'S LOCAL CHAPTER, WHO HAS ALSO RECEIVED DEATH THREATS IN THE PAST FEW HOURS.

THIS IS WHAT BALZA TOLD RADIO CHILENA'S "PRIMERA PLANA" FEATURE:

[BALZA] [BEGIN RECORDING] UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS ATTACKED THE PDC'S PREMISES, LOCATED AT 683 SOTOMAYOR STREET, BREAKING THE WINDOWS OF THE PREMISES AND TRYING TO BREAK DOWN THE DOOR. LUCKILY, OUR GUARD WENT OUTSIDE TO SEE WHAT WAS HAPPENING AND THE ATTACKERS TOOK OFF, LEAVING ABUNDANT YES-VOTE PROPAGANDA WITH THE PHOTOGRAPH OF THE CANDIDATE. THE ATTACKERS ALSO SHOUTED THREATS AGAINST THE MEMBERS OF THE PARTY'S BOARD.

WE HAVE ALREADY TOLD THE ARICA PUBLIC, BUT NOW WE WANT ALL OF THE CHILEAN PUBLIC TO KNOW, THAT THE SUPPORTERS OF THE YES-VOTE ARE DESPERATE, BECAUSE THEY SEE THERE ARE NOW MORE NO-VOTE SUPPORTERS THAN YES-VOTE SUPPORTERS.

THIS IS WHY THE LATTER ARE THREATENING PEOPLE, WHY THEY ARE TRYING TO STEAL IDENTITY CARDS, AND WHY THEY ARE RESORTIG TO ANY TYPE OF ACTION THAT WILL CREATE UNREST IN ORDER TO GIVE CONFIDENCE TO THE SUPPORTERS OF THE YES-VOTE AND TO CREATE AN ATMOSPHERE FOR ANY TYPE OF ACTION TO BE TAKEN ON 5 OCTOBER. [END RECORDING] [PASSAGE OMITTED]

TST4-MUC4-0027

LIMA, 15 SEP 88 (EL COMERCIO) -- [TEXT] THE POLICE HAVE ARRESTED JUAN ANTONIO LEON MONTERO, AKA COMRADE JOSE, WHO IS REGARDED AS AN IMPORTANT MEMBER OF A TERRORIST COLUMN THAT CONDUCTED ATTACKS IN THE SAN MARTIN JUNGLE UNDER THE LEADERSHIP OF TERRORIST VICTOR POLAY CAMPOS, AKA COMRADE ROLANDO.

THE DIRCOTE [ANTITERRORIST DIRECTORATE] HAS ALSO REPORTED THAT LEON TOOK PART IN TERRORIST ATTACKS WITH NESTOR SERPA CARTOLINI, ANOTHER TOP MRTA LEADER.

ACCORDING TO INVESTIGATIONS, A SO-CALLED COMRADE LUCHO CONVINCED COMRADE JOSE TO JOIN THE MRTA IN JULY 1986.

UNTIL MARCH 1987 LEON DISTRIBUTED LEAFLETS ON STREETS AND SQUARES, PAINTED SLOGANS ON THE WALLS OF PUBLIC BUILDINGS, AND DELIVERED FOOD--WHICH WAS STOLEN FROM WELL-KNOWN BUSINESS FIRMS--IN SHANTYTOWNS.

IN MID-AUGUST 1987, LEON GOT INTO TOUCH WITH COMRADE MARIO, WITH WHOM HE TRAVELED TO THE VILLAGE OF TARAPOTO TO JOIN THE MRTA NORTHEASTERN COLUMN LED BY POLAY CAMPOS AND EMILIO SALAS SALDANA, AKA COMRADE MOISES, AMONG OTHERS.

AS A MEMBER OF THE MRTA, LEON PARTICIPATED IN THE ATTACK AGAINST THE CIVIL GUARD POSTS OF TABALOZOS, SAN MARTIN, AND SOLITOR. DURING THE FIRST HALF OF NOVEMBER, HE PARTICIPATED IN AN ATTACK ON THE GC [CIVIL GUARD] IN THE TOWNSHIP OF JUANJUI.

DURING THIS ATTACK, GC LIEUTENANT JORGE CIEZA LACHO WAS KILLED BY THE MRTA TERRORISTS, WHO ALSO SEIZED LARGE AMOUNTS OF WEAPONS, AMMUNITION, AND GRENADES. A FEW HOURS LATER THE TERRORISTS ATTACKED THE VILLAGE OF SAN JOSE DE SISA.

LEON WAS ARRESTED IN LIMA BY DIRCOTE PERSONNEL. LEON HAD BEEN KEPT UNDER SURVEILLANCE FOR SEVERAL MONTHS AFTER HIS RETURN FROM THE JUNGLE, WHERE THE MRTA WAS PRACTICALLY ANNIHILATED BY THE ARMY.

LEON WAS PLACED AT THE DISPOSAL OF THE COURT ON TERRORIST CHARGES.

TST4-MUC4-0028

SANTIAGO, 3 OCT 88 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] A TERRORIST ATTACK, IN WHICH CZECHOSLOVAK BOMBS WERE USED, HAS DESTROYED FOUR HIGH TENSION TOWERS IN THE CENTRAL REGION. THIS ATTACK HAS CUT THE ELECTRICITY SUPPLY TO A VAST REGION BETWEEN COPIAPO AND SANTIAGO. THE BLACKOUT OCCURRED ON SATURDAY NIGHT, 1 OCTOBER, AND LASTED FOR APPROXIMATELY ONE-HALF HOUR IN THE METROPOLITAN REGION.

ACCORDING TO ENDESA [NATIONAL ELECTRIC POWER, INC.], ONE OF THE TOWERS KNOCKED DOWN WAS LOCATED ON KM 24 OF THE MELIPILLA-RAPEL HIGHWAY.

THE TOWER, LOCATED IN THE MAITENES SECTOR, IS ONE OF THE MAIN TOWERS OF THE HIGH TENSION NETWORK.

ANOTHER TOWER DESTROYED BY THE TERRORISTS WAS TOWER NO 430 IN THE ITAHUA-ALTO JAHUEL SECTOR, WHICH IS CONNECTED TO THE MAIN ELECTRICITY NETWORK.

IN ADDITION TO THESE FOUR DESTROYED TOWERS, OTHER EXPLOSIONS WERE HEARD THAT SAME NIGHT IN SANTIAGO. THEY WERE CAUSED BY BOMBS PLANTED BY TERRORISTS WHO SEEK TO FRIGHTEN THE POPULATION.

ACCORDING TO POLICE SOURCES, THE BOMBS USED TO CAUSE SO MUCH DAMAGE ARE POWERFUL CZECHOSLOVAK-MADE PLASTIC BOMBS, OF THE SAME TYPE THAT WERE FOUND AMONG THE CLANDESTINE ARSENALS SMUGGLED INTO THE COUNTRY BY THE MARXIST LEFTISTS AT CARRIZAL BAJO.

THE TERRORISTS ALSO USED TNT IN THEIR BOMB ATTACKS.

TST4-MUC4-0031

BOGOTA, 7 OCT 88 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] AN EXPLOSION HAS DESTROYED A SECTION OF THE MULTIPURPOSE PIPELINE RUNNING FROM BARRANCABERMEJA TO BUCARAMANGA. THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED IN ALTO DE SAN PABLO WHILE GASOLINE AND PROPANE GAS WERE BEING PUMPED TO BUCARAMANGA. WE HAVE A REPORT NOW FROM TERESA RUEDA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [RUEDA] COMMUNICATIONS TO AND FROM PUERTO PETROLERO AND BUCARAMANGA HAVE BEEN CUT OFF SINCE EARLY TODAY, AFTER AN ATTEMPT TO DYNAMITE THE MULTIPURPOSE PIPELINE DESTROYED A 100-METER SECTION OF THE CENTRAL HIGHWAY.

THE SUPPLY OF GAS TO BUCARAMANGA WILL ALSO BE AFFECTED BY THIS EVENT. IT IS ESTIMATED THAT IT WILL TAKE AT LEAST 3 DAYS TO RESTORE NORMAL TRAFFIC, BECAUSE IT WILL BE NECESSARY TO USE DYNAMITE TO REMOVE ROCKS CURRENTLY BLOCKING THE HIGHWAY.

THE ATTEMPTED SABOTAGE OCCURRED AT THE 65-KM MARK ON THE BUCARAMANGA - BARRANCABERMEJA HIGHWAY, 20 KM FROM THE PLACE WHERE A MILITARY CONVOY WAS AMBUSHED LAST WEDNESDAY. THIS IS THE SECOND TIME THAT AN ATTEMPTED SABOTAGE OF THE BUCARAMANGA - BARRANCABERMEJA MULTIPURPOSE PIPELINE, WHICH CARRIES PROPANE GAS, GASOLINE, AND ACPM [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] HAS TAKEN PLACE. THE EXPLOSION DESTROYED A 30-METER SECTION OF PIPELINE, AND SPARKED A FIRE THAT HAS NOT YET BEEN EXTINGUISHED.

LOSSES CAUSED BY THE SABOTAGE, WHICH HAS BEEN ATTRIBUTED TO THE ELN, HAVE YET TO BE ASCERTAINED. IT IS ESTIMATED THAT REPAIRS TO THE HIGHWAY ALONE WILL COST THE PUBLIC WORKS MINISTRY 5 MILLION PESOS.

[ISMAEL OROZCO, PUBLIC WORKS DIRECTOR FOR THE 5TH DISTRICT] WELL, AFTER INITIAL TALKS WITH ECOPETROL [COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE] TECHNICIANS TODAY, BEGINNING AT 1700, AFTER THE FIRE IS UNDER CONTROL, THEY WILL BEGIN RESTORING SERVICE ON THE OIL PIPELINE.

[RUEDA] AT THIS TIME, THERE IS TRAFFIC CONGESTION NEAR THE SUGAMOSO BRIDGE. [END RECORDING] [PASSAGE OMITTED]

WHILE STILL ON THE SUBJECT, ECOPETROL'S PRESIDENT, WHO TRAVELED THIS MORNING TO BARRANCABERMEJA TO ATTEND A FORUM ON THE MAGDALENA RIVER, REPORTED THAT, SO FAR THIS YEAR, TERRORIST ATTACKS HAVE COST HIS COMPANY $300 MILLION. WE HAVE THIS REPORT FROM MARIA CLARA GRACIA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GRACIA] ECOPETROL HAS LOST 95 BILLION PESOS IN REVENUES THIS YEAR DUE TO THE 44 TERRORIST ATTACKS ON THE CANO LIMON - COVENAS OIL PIPELINE. IN THESE ATTACKS, 13.2 MILLION BARRELS OF CRUDE OIL HAVE BEEN LOST. THE AREAS MOST AFFECTED BY THESE ATTACKS ARE IN SUCRE, ARAUCA, NORTE DE SANTANDER, AND SANTANDER DEPARTMENTS.

[REPORTER ALVARO AYALA] DOCTOR, COULD THESE TERRORIST ATTACKS LEAD TO AN INCREASE IN FUEL PRICES IN COLOMBIA?

[DR ANDRES RESTREPO LONDONO, PRESIDENT OF ECOPETROL] OBVIOUSLY, THERE WILL COME A TIME WHEN, FACED WITH INCREASING INTERNAL PRODUCTION COSTS AND FALLING REVENUES, WE ARE GOING TO HAVE TO CONSIDER COMPENSATING OUR LOSSES WITH AN INCREASE IN DOMESTIC OIL PRICES, BUT THAT IS A MEASURE WE ARE NOT ABOUT TO ADOPT AT THIS TIME.

[GRACIA] TODAY'S LANDSLIDE, WHICH DESTROYED A SECTION OF THE MULTIPURPOSE PIPELINE BETWEEN BARRANCABERMEJA AND BUCARAMANGA, HAS RESULTED IN ESTIMATED LOSSES TOTALLING 1.435 BILLION PESOS. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

TST4-MUC4-0035

BELMOPAN (BELIZE), 24 NOV 88 (BRIDGETOWN CANA) -- [TEXT] BELIZE'S STATE RADIO ON THURSDAY REPORTED THAT A GUATEMALAN GUNBOAT FIRED AT A BRITISH NAVAL VESSEL THAT HAS BEEN CONDUCTING A SURVEY IN BELIZE'S WATERS. THE RADIO SAID THE INCIDENT OCCURRED LAST SUNDAY IN THE WATERS OFF SOUTHERN BELIZE.

THE REPORT SAID THAT THE HMS FAWN, WHICH HAS BEEN CONDUCTING HOLOGRAPHIC SURVEYS, WAS REPORTEDLY IN BELIZEAN TERRITORIAL WATERS--NEAR THE MEDIAN LINE WHERE THE SEA BOUNDARIES OF HONDURAS, BELIZE AND GUATEMALA MEET--WHEN "A GUATEMALAN GUNBOAT ORDERED THE SHIP TO STOP." THE INSTRUCTION WAS IGNORED, THE RADIO SAID, "WHEREUPON THE GUATEMALAN VESSEL FIRED A SHOT IN THE DIRECTION OF THE BRITISH SURVEY VESSEL."

THE BRITISH DISPATCHED TWO ROYAL AIRFORCE FIGHTER PLANES TO THE "GENERAL AREA AND ONCE THE BRITISH HARRIERS APPEARED AT THE SITE OF THE INCIDENT, THE BRITISH COMMUNICATED BY TELEPHONE WITH GUATEMALAN AUTHORITIES," THE RADIO REPORTED. AGREEMENT WAS REACHED FOR THE GUATEMALAN VESSEL TO WITHDRAW FROM THE AREA.

BRITISH AUTHORITIES HAVE TAKEN UP THE MATTER WITH GUATEMALA AND TRUST THAT GUATEMALAN AUTHORITIES WILL TAKE MEASURES TO ENSURE "THAT AN UNFORTUNATE AND DANGEROUS INCIDENT" WHICH OCCURRED ON SUNDAY "WILL NOT RECUR," THE RADIO SAID.

IN EARLY OCTOBER THE GUATEMALAN NAVAL PATROL IN THE SAME GENERAL AREA IN THE SOUTH OF BELIZE, SEIZED A HONDURAS REGISTERED BOAT ALONG WITH ITS HONDURAN CREW AND FIVE BELIZEANS INCLUDING FIVE FISHERMEN AND A MARINE BIOLOGIST WHO WERE CONDUCTING DEEP SEA FISHING RESEARCH IN THE AREA. THE BELIZEANS WERE LATER RELEASED AFTER THE BELIZE GOVERNMENT APPROACHED GUATEMALAN AUTHORITIES. BELIZE PRIME MINISTER MANUAL ESQUIVEL LATER TOLD A PRESS CONFERENCE THAT THE HONDURAN VESSEL WAS IN GUATEMALAN WATERS WHEN IT WAS SEIZED.

RELATIONS BETWEEN BELIZE AND GUATEMALA HAVE BEEN STRAINED BY THEIR TERRITORIAL DISPUTE. GUATEMALA CLAIMS A SECTION OF BELIZE--A CLAIM WHICH THE FORMER BRITISH COLONY REJECTED.

TST4-MUC4-0038

TEGUCIGALPA, 15 OCT 88 (EL HERALDO) -- [TEXT] HONDURAN MILITARY SOURCES YESTERDAY REPORTED THAT SEVERAL TIMES IN SEPTEMBER, EPS SOLDIERS ENTERED HONDURAN TERRITORY AND HARASSED THE 6TH INFANTRY BATTALION OBSERVATION POST IN EL PITAL, CIFUENTES, EL PARAISO DEPARTMENT.

THE RAIDS INTO HONDURAN TERRITORY AND THE HARASSMENTS OCCURRED AS FOLLOWS:

1. ON 19 AUGUST 1988, EPS TROOPS SET UP COMMUNICATIONS TRACKING EQUIPMENT (RADAR) IN LOMA FRIA, WHICH WAS PROTECTED BY MISSILES AND ANTIAIRCRAFT MACHINEGUNS.

2. ON 21 AUGUST 1988, EPS SOLDIERS KIDNAPPED HONDURAN CITIZENS ROSALIO MEJIA RODRIGUEZ AND HER SON GUILLERMO SAUL MEJIA HERRERA, WHO WERE TAKEN TO NICARAGUAN TERRITORY.

3. ON 6 SEPTEMBER 1988, AN EPS PATROL ENTERED HONDURAN TERRITORY AND HARASSED THE 6TH INFANTRY BATTALION POSTS LOCATED IN EL PITAL, CIFUENTES. OUR TROOPS RESPONDED TO THEIR FIRE AND SUFFERED NO CASUALTIES.

4. ON 9 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS SOLDIERS ATTACKED WITH MACHINEGUN AND MORTAR FIRE THE 9TH INFANTRY BRIGADE BATTALION POST IN CERRO PELON, LA LAMPARA, QUEBRADA DEL ORO, AND TAPALCHI, IN POTECA RIVER, PARAISO. DURING THE ATTACK, SOLDIER JOSE MARIO CHICAS DIAZ WAS WOUNDED. OUR TROOPS RESPONDED TO THE FIRE AND REPORTED NO [FURTHER] CASUALTIES.

5. ON 10 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS TROOPS CONTINUED ATTACKING THE SAME 9TH INFANTRY BRIGADE BATTALION POST WITH 50-MM MACHINEGUNS; PATROLS WERE INCREASED AND PERSONNEL AND WEAPONS WERE DEPLOYED TO THE GUAPINOL, COMARCA, PARAISITO, AND COMARCA GUANITO SECTORS, NEAR THE POTECA RIVER.

6. ON 14 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS SOLDIERS HARASSED WITH MACHINEGUN FIRE THE 9TH INFANTRY BRIGADE POST LOCATED IN EL GUINEO AND PUEBLO NUEVO, CIFUENTES. NO CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED.

7. ON 18 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS SOLDIERS ATTACKED POSITIONS HELD BY THE 9TH INFANTRY BATTALION AT LA CONGOLONA ON THE POTECA RIVER WITH 82 - AND 120-MM MORTARS, RPG-7'S, AND RIFLE FIRE. THE FIRE WAS RETURNED WITHOUT ANY REPORTED CASUALTIES.

8. ON 19 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS SOLDIERS ATTACKED, WITH MORTARS, RIFLE, AND RPG-7'S, POSITIONS HELD BY THE 6TH INFANTRY BATTALION IN EL PITAL, AND ALSO IN ADUENA VIEJA, GUASAPO, AND CIFUENTES. OUR TROOPS RETURNED THE FIRE WITHOUT ANY REPORTED CASUALTIES.

9. ON 20 SEPTEMBER 1988, THE EPS FREED HECTOR ROSALES MEJIA RODRIGUEZ AND HIS SON GUILLERMO SAUL MEJIA HERRERA, WHO HAD BEEN KIDNAPPED BY EPS TROOPS ON 21 AUGUST 1988.

10. ON 24 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS TROOPS HARASSAED WITH RIFLE FIRE A 6TH INFANTRY BATTALION POSITION IN ADUANA VIEJA, CIFUENTES, WITHOUT ANY REPORTED CASUALTIES.

11. ON 25 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS TROOPS HARASSED ADUANA CIFUENTES WITH RIFLE FIRE, WITHOUT ANY REPORTED CASUALTIES.

12. ON 25 SEPTEMBER 1988, EPS TROOPS SHOT A 120-MM MORTAR THAT FELL 75 METERS FROM CASA DE LADRILLO IN CIFUENTES.

TST4-MUC4-0039

BOGOTA, 17 OCT 88 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE LEFTIST NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY (ELN) KIDNAPPED TWO SOLDIERS IN NORTHERN COLOMBIA IN THE PAST FEW HOURS. THIS BRINGS TO 24 THE NUMBER OF MILITARY MEN HELD BY REBELS.

ACCORDING TO 2D BRIGADE COMMANDER GENERAL JUAN SALCEDO LORA, THE SOLDIERS ARE ARTILLERY BATTALION MEMBERS AND WERE KIDNAPPED WHILE WORKING ON A HIGHWAY IN POPONTE, IN THE NORTHERN CESAR DEPARTMENT.

MEANWHILE, AN OFFICER AND FOUR POLICEMEN ARE EXPECTED TO BE RELEASED IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS. THE FARC KIDNAPPED THESE MEN 6 WEEKS AGO WHEN THE REBELS ATTACKED MINCA IN THE SIERRA NEVADA DE SANTA MARTA AREA.

AN OFFICIAL COMMITTEE, FORMED BY GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS FROM THE NATIONAL REHABILITATION PLAN AND THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE AND MEMBERS OF THE "DEMOCRATIC COEXISTENCE COMMISSION"--A MULTIPARTY ORGANIZATION THAT SEARCHES FOR POLITICAL SOLUTIONS TO COLOMBIA'S PROBLEMS--WAS CONTACTING THE REBELS TODAY TO WORK OUT THE FINAL DETAILS OF THE FIVE MILITARY MEN'S RELEASE.

THE REMAINING 17 POLICEMEN--TAKEN BY THE REBELS DURING AN ATTACK ON NORTHERN SAN PABLO MUNICIPALITY ON 5 OCTOBER--ARE STILL HELD BY THE REBELS. TALKS FOR THEIR RELEASE HAVE NOT MOVED FORWARD BECAUSE THE ARMY REFUSES TO ACCEPT THIRD PARTIES AS MEDIATORS.

TST4-MUC4-0040

CLANDESTINE, 19 OCT 88 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [EXCERPTS] ATTENTION: THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE URBAN COMMAND HAS BRILLIANTLY SABOTAGED A COMMERCIAL BUILDING BELONGING TO THE BOURGEOISIE IN THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, CAUSING HEAVY ECONOMIC LOSSES TO THE IDLE CLASS. AT LEAST 37 BUSINESSES WERE DESTROYED.

THE SAME URBAN COMMAND CARRIED OUT OTHER SABOTAGE AT THE [NAME INDISTINCT] PARKING LOT--SPECIFICALLY, IN THE PINK ZONE, OR ACTUALLY IN WHAT SHOULD BE CALLED THE RED ZONE. OTHER SABOTAGE TOOK PLACE AT THE LANCER MOTEL NEAR APOPA.

IN A COMMUNIQUE, THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE URBAN COMMAND STATES THAT ON 15 SEPTEMBER, A LENGTHY ORGANIZATIONAL PROCESS TO CREATE A NEW POLITICAL-MILITARY GROUP--IN WHICH 25 DELEGATIONS REPRESENTING NEIGHBORHOOD COMMANDS PARTICIPATED--ENDED WITH THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE URBAN COMMAND.

THE COMMUNIQUE WARNS THE ARMY HIGH COMMAND, ITS OFFICERS, CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC AND ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] OFFICIALS, AND U.S. ADVISERS THAT THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE URBAN COMMAND IS A WEAPON THAT WILL BE USED AGAINST THEM WHEREVER THEY MAY BE--AT HOME, WORK, AND AT RECREATION AND CORRUPTION CENTERS. IN ADDITION, THEIR PROPERTY HAS BEEN DECLARED PERMAMENT MILITARY TARGETS UNTIL THEY STOP THE BLOODSHED AGAINST THE PEOPLE. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

IN THE PAST FEW HOURS, THE FMLN'S PEDRO PABLO CASTILLO URBAN COMMAND EXECUTED AN AIR FORCE OFFICER AS PART OF THE "MURDER THE CRIMINALS" OPERATION AGAINST REPRESSION, THE MASSACRE IN SAN VICENTE, AND THE PERSECUTION OF THE UNIVERSITY COMMUNITY.

THE EXECUTION OF AN AIR FORCE PILOT OFFICER WAS CARRIED OUT IN SAN SALVADOR'S LAS BRISAS NEIGHBORHOOD. WE CAN IMAGINE THE HAPPINESS OF OUR PEOPLE UPON HEARING THE NEWS THAT ONE OF THE CRIMINALS AMONG CRIMINALS--THAT IS, ONE OF THE PILOTS WHO HAVE BOMBED VILLAGES AND CANTONS THROUGHOUT OUR FATHERLAND--WAS KILLED AS A RESULT OF REVOLUTIONARY JUSTICE. FROM NOW ON, BOMBS WILL NOT ONLY EXPLODE IN THE VILLAGES OF CHALATENANGO, CABANAS, USULUTAN, MORAZAN, AND NORTHERN SAN MIGUEL; MORE POWERFUL BOMBS WILL NOW EXPLODE MORE FREQUENTLY IN THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS, THAT IS, IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE RICH, IN THEIR RECREATION CENTERS, MANSIONS, AND WHEREVER ELSE THEY MAY GO.

TST4-MUC4-0042

BOGOTA, 24 OCT 88 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO MILITARY SOURCES, A BLOODY GUERRRILLA OFFENSIVE TODAY LEFT 35 GUERRILLAS AND 5 SOLDIERS DEAD, 6 CIVILIANS WOUNDED, AND 5 BRIDGES PARTIALLY DESTROYED.

THE OUTBREAK OF THE VIOLENCE COINCIDED WITH THE REPLY FROM ALL THE REBEL GROUPS TO AN OFFICIAL PEACE PLAN AND WITH THE CONFIRMATION BY THE LABOR FEDERATIONS THAT THEY WILL HOLD A GENERAL STRIKE ON THURSDAY DESPITE GOVERNMENT EFFORTS TO PREVENT IT.

THE SO-CALLED NATIONAL GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD (CNG) PROPOSED TO PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO THE HOLDING OF A SUMMIT BETWEEN THE REBEL LEADERS AND THE GOVERNMENT, DEFENSE, AND ENERGY AND MINES MINISTERS AT A PLACE AND DATE TO BE AGREED UPON.

THE DOCUMENT PROPOSED THAT THE MEDIATOR OF THE DIALOGUE BE THE DEMOCRATIC COEXISTENCE COMMISSION [COMISION DE CONVIVENCIA DEMOCRATICA], HEADED BY MSGR DARIO CASTRILLON, PRESIDENT OF THE LATIN AMERICAN BISHOPS CONFERENCE. THE DOCUMENT IS VIEWED AS THE CNG'S OFFICIAL REPLY TO THE GOVERNMENT'S PEACE PLAN.

GUERRILLAS OF THE FARC AND THE POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY (EPL) ATTACKED FOUR TOWNS IN NORTHERN COLOMBIA, LEAVING 17 GUERRILLAS AND 2 SOLDIERS DEAD AND 3 BRIDGES PARTIALLY DESTROYED.

THE DEFENSE MINISTRY REPORTED THAT FARC GUERRILLAS AMBUSHED A MILITARY CONVOY IN HUILA DEPARTMENT, KILLING THREE SOLDIERS. IT ALSO REPORTED THAT THREE REBELS WERE KILLED IN CLASHES IN SOUTHERN COLOMBIA.

IT ADDED THAT NINE GUERRILLAS OF THE ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION WERE KILLED IN CLASHES WITH TROOPS OF THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE ON THE BORDER OF ANTIOQUIA AND CHOCO DEPARTMENTS AND THAT SIX FARC REBELS WERE KILLED IN CAQUETA DEPARTMENT.

SUSPECTED GUERRILLAS DYNAMITED AT DUSK A BRIDGE IN BOGOTA'S URBAN CENTER, INJURING SIX PEOPLE. THE BRIDGE DID NOT SUSTAIN MAJOR DAMAGE. ANOTHER BRIDGE WAS BLOWN UP IN SANTANDER DEPARTMENT.

MILITARY SOURCES SAID THESE WERE REBEL ACTIONS IN SUPPORT OF THE STRIKE AND THEY CHARGED THAT WORKERS, PEASANTS, AND BUS DRIVERS ARE BEING THREATENED TO FORCE THEM TO JOIN THE STRIKE.

PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO HEADED A MEETING OF THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL TO ADOPT MEASURES TO PREVENT DISORDERS DURING THE PLANNED STRIKE AND TO GUARANTEE PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION FOR THE PEOPLE.

THE GOVERNMENT AND THE WORKERS YESTERDAY BROKE OFF THEIR TALKS AFTER BEING UNABLE TO REACH AGREEMENT ON AN INCREASE OF THE MINIMUM WAGE AND ON A FREEZE IN THE PRICES OF STAPLES.

THE STRIKE, CALLED BY THE UNITED WORKERS CONFEDERATION AND THE GENERAL CONFEDERATION OF LABOR, WILL PROTEST THE FACT THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT REPLIED TO LABOR DEMANDS THEY PRESENTED IN MAY.

TST4-MUC4-0043

SAN SALVADOR, 24 OCT 88 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT BY ISABEL RUIZ ON STATEMENTS BY NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) LEADER SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ] [EXCERPTS] [PASSAGE OMITTED] [OCHOA] [BEGIN RECORDING] WE ARE FACING AN ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE CAUSED BY THE FMLN, WHICH SHOWS ITS MILITARY WEAKNESS MORE THAN ANYTHING ELSE. THE FMLN IS SUPPOSEDLY ATTACKING MILITARY TARGETS, BUT NEITHER A JAIL NOR A SHOPPING MALL IS A MILITARY TARGET. COMMERCIAL AREAS OR AMUSEMENT PLACES ARE NOT MILITARY TARGETS. CAR BOMBS WENT OFF IN SUCH PLACES LATELY. THEY WENT OFF AT A CHAIN OF [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND AT A SHOPPING MALL. THE FMLN'S STRATEGY IS SIMPLY TO INCREASE ITS TERRORIST ACTIONS.

FOR THAT REASON, IT IS REGRETTABLE THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DESCRIBES THE FMLN AS A GROUP IN ARMS, BECAUSE THEY ARE MERELY TERRORIST CRIMINALS. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THERE IS POLITICAL WEAKNESS, BECAUSE THE ARMED FORCES ARE NOT GIVEN CLEAR MISSIONS. WE SEE THE ACTIONS OF THE ARMED FORCES AND THE SECURITY CORPS ARE FRUSTRATED, BECAUSE THEY SPEND TIME, EFFORT, AND MEN CAPTURING TERRORISTS WHILE THE GOVERNMENT SUBSEQUENTLY RELEASES THEM FOR HUMANITARIAN REASONS.

I BELIEVE THE GOVERNMENT MUST APPLY THE LAWS MORE FORCEFULLY AND STOP DECEIVING THE POPULATION WITH WORDS SUCH AS DEMOCRATIZATION AND WITH ITS GREAT POLITICAL DEMAGOGY. [END RECORDING]

FINALLY, OCHOA PEREZ CRITICIZED THE MEETING COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS WILL HOLD WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND TODAY. HE SAID OSCAR ARIAS IS NOT THE RIGHT PERSON TO DEAL WITH SALVADORAN INTERNAL AFFAIRS.

TST4-MUC4-0044

SANTIAGO, 16 OCT 88 (EL MERCURIO) -- [TEXT] THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT (FPMR) WILL DEVELOP A NEW FORM OF STRUGGLE CALLED THE "NATIONAL PATRIOTIC WAR," "WHICH WILL START AT ANY MOMENT."

THIS INFORMATION WAS DISCLOSED YESTERDAY TO EL MERCURIO BY FPMR SPOKESMAN VICTOR DIAZ CARO, WHO SAID THAT THE TRUCE DURING THE PLEBISCITE WAS TO PREPARE THE PHASE THEY ARE NOW STARTING.

HE ALSO CONFIRMED THE STATEMENT IN BRUSSELS THIS WEEK BY FPMR INTERNATIONAL SPOKESMAN MARCELO REYES.

DIAZ CARO, WHO HAS CONFESSED TO BEING ONE OF THE SNIPERS WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE ATTACK ON PRESIDENT AUGUSTO PINOCHET, IS CURRENTLY UNDER ARREST IN THE SANTIAGO PRISON, AND, TOGETHER WITH VASILY CARILLO NOVA, HE IS NATIONAL SPOKESMAN FOR ONE OF THE FACTIONS OF THIS EXTREMIST ORGANIZATION.

DIAZ CARO, WHO WAS ARRESTED IN LATE 1986 BY THE POLICE, ANNOUNCED THAT IN "A MATTER OF HOURS" THEY WILL START SUBVERSIVE ACTIONS. HE EXPLAINED THAT THIS NEW PHASE OF ARMED STRUGGLE WILL BE CARRIED OUT "FROM ARICA DOWN TO MAGALLANES."

AT THE SAME TIME HE REFERRED TO THE RESULTS OF THE PLEBISCITE, STATING THAT ALTHOUGH THEY RESPECT THOSE WHO VOTED "NO," "THE ONLY ASPECT OF THE VICTORY OF THE `NO' WE ACCEPT IS THAT PINOCHET LEAVE POWER."

IN REFERRING TO THE FPMR'S CHANGE OF STRATEGY, DIAZ CARO DISCLOSED THAT THE DECISION WAS MADE DURING A MEETING OF THE ORGANIZATION'S LEADERS LAST APRIL.

OF THIS OCCASION THEY DISCUSSED THE LINE THAT THE TERRORIST ORGANIZATION SHOULD FOLLOW. THEY ALSO DECIDED TO GIVE UP THE IDEA OF AN "ARMED REBELLION," WHICH PREVAILED UNTIL THEN. THE MAIN CHARACTERISTIC OF THAT IDEA WAS THAT THE ORGANIZATION SERVED TO COMPLEMENT CLASS STRUGGLE (AS IT DID IN ITS ORIGIN IN 1983), TO SUPPORT THE PEOPLE'S REBELLION TO PARALYZE THE COUNTRY AND TO PERPETRATE ATTACKS AGAINST THE ESTABLISHED REGIME.

DIAZ CARO DISCLOSED THAT DURING THE MEETING THEY DECIDED TO REPLACE THE REBELLION WITH THE SEARCH FOR A PATRIOTIC UNITY GOVERNMENT. HE SAID THAT "WE REALIZE THAT OUSTING THE REGIME IS SUBJECT TO NEGOTIATIONS UNDER A PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENT."

ACCORDING TO DIAZ CARO THIS IS WHEN THEY REALIZED THE "NEED FOR A `TRUCE' BECAUSE THEY NEEDED TO PLAN GREATER STEPS."

HE ADDED THAT "THIS IS WHEN WHAT WE CALL THE `NATIONAL PATRIOTIC WAR' SURFACED. THE MAIN ISSUE OF THIS WAR IS THE ARMED STRUGGLE; WE ARE NO LONGER A MERE COMPLEMENT TO THE PEOPLE. IT REPRESENTS A QUALITATIVE STEP FORWARD AND ENTAILS GREATER RESPONSIBILITIES."

DIAZ CARO DISCLOSED THAT THIS NEW PHASE WILL REQUIRE A GREATER QUANTITY OF WEAPONS, MORE MEN, AND ALL THE SUPPORT NECESSARY TO OPERATE. HE SAID THAT THE MONTHS OF TRUCE WERE USED TO FULFILL THESE NEEDS.

THE SPOKESMAN ADDED THAT DURING THE MEETING THEY ALSO DECIDED ON THE NEED TO ESTABLISH A NON-ISOLATED ACTION. "WE THOUGHT THAT ACTIONS IN SANTIAGO, CONCEPCION, AND VALPARAISO WOULD BE THE SOLUTION, BUT THAT WAS NOT THE CASE."

DIAZ CARO EXPLAINED THAT "THIS IS WHY WE NOW REALIZE THAT THE STRUGGLE SHOULD BE CARRIED OUT FROM ARICA DOWN TO MAGALLANES, THROUGHOUT THE TERRITORY AND IN VARIOUS FORMS." [CONTINUED]

TST4-MUC4-0046

SAN SALVADOR, 26 OCT 88 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMENTS ON THE AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL REPORT, WHICH CLAIMS THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE INVOLVED IN THE MURDER OF CERTAIN SALVADORAN CITIZENS?

[DUARTE] I UNDERSTAND THAT AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL HAS TO PREPARE A REPORT EVERY YEAR, AND THE ORGANIZATION INCLUDES WHATEVER VIEWS IT CHOOSES IN THE REPORT. THE ORGANIZATION OBVIOUSLY STATES ITS VIEWS IN THE REPORT. SALVADORANS DO THINGS ACCORDING TO THE LAW. IF ANY SALVADORAN OR FOREIGNER HAS EVIDENCE [OF HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS], THEN IT SHOULD BE BROUGHT BEFORE THE COURTS. THAT IS THE LOGICAL AND LEGAL WAY FOR US TO BEGIN AN INVESTIGATION; THAT IS WHAT WE ALWAYS DO IN ALL SUCH CASES.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, YOUR GOVERNMENT HAS ISSUED A SPECIAL REPORT CLAIMING THAT SOME DEATH SQUAD MEMBERS HAVE DESERTED AND IMPLICATED SEVERAL RIGHT-WING MEMBERS IN THE MURDER OF MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO AND OTHER SALVADORANS.

[DUARTE] WE ARE ANALYZING THE AVAILABLE EVIDENCE IN THOSE CASES. YOU KNOW THAT I HAVE CAREFULLY ANALYZED THE CASES. I RELEASED INFORMATION ONLY WHEN THE EVIDENCE WAS DULY INVESTIGATED AND CORROBORATED. WE ARE PROCESSING A SIZABLE AMOUNT OF INFORMATION, BUT I DO NOT WANT TO DISCUSS IT IN DETAIL BECAUSE I BELIEVE THAT THIS WOULD HINDER THE INVESTIGATION.

[REPORTER] IS IT TRUE THAT YOU HAVE TWO VIDEO RECORDINGS IN WHICH THE TWO DESERTERS GIVE THEIR NAMES AND DETAILS AND THAT THESE RECORDINGS ARE BEING ANALYZED BY MILITARY INTELLIGENCE SERVICES AND THE GOVERNMENT?

[DUARTE] WE ARE CURRENTLY INVESTIGATING THE CASE. THAT IS WHY I SAID THAT I WOULD NOT LIKE TO REVEAL ANY DETAILED INFORMATION--BECAUSE THIS MIGHT HINDER THE INVESTIGATION.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, THE AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL REPORT STATES THAT DEATH SQUADS--WHICH ARE REPORTEDLY COMPOSED OF SOLDIERS AND POLICEMEN--ARE BEING REACTIVATED AT A TIME WHEN THE ARMED FORCES OPPOSE YOUR POLICIES.

[DUARTE] I DO NOT THINK SO. MY GOVERNMENT'S POLICY REMAINS UNCHANGED. WE ADVOCATE THE DEFENSE OF HUMAN RIGHTS AND DEMOCRACY. I THINK THIS IS ALWAYS EVIDENT. EVERY DAY THIS IS DEMONSTRATED BY EVENTS. [WORDS INDISTINCT] FILM ABOUT GUERRILLA COMMANDERS, WHICH REPRESENTS SUPPORT FOR THE FMLN AND DISTORTS THE PEOPLE'S VIEWS. NEVERTHELESS, WE KNOW THAT FREEDOM OF THE PRESS MUST PREVAIL AND THEREFORE WE DO NOT INTERVENE. YOU WILL NOT FIND ANOTHER COUNTRY THAT DOES THIS, YET WE ARE DOING SO BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAT WE SHOULD DEFEND FREEDOM OF THE PRESS ABOVE ALL.

[REPORTER] HOW MUCH CREDENCE DO YOU GIVE THE AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL REPORT?

[DUARTE] THE REPORT IS VALID INSOFAR AS THE FACTS ARE ALL THERE. HOWEVER, I [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE WAY IN WHICH THE FACTS ARE INTERPRETED. THE FACTS ARE INTERPRETED ACCORDING TO AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL'S OWN [WORD INDISTINCT]. WE ALSO RECEIVED REPORTS FROM RED CROSS INTERNATIONAL [WORDS INDISTINCT] EACH CASE. EACH CASE IS INTERPRETED DIFFERENTLY. THE UNITED NATIONS HAS ITS OWN OPINION; THE OAS HAS ITS OWN OPINION. EACH ONE ISSUES A REPORT, AND WE USE THAT INFORMATION AS THE BASIS FOR OUR INVESTIGATIONS ON HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS, WHICH IS THE MAIN ISSUE. [END RECORDING]

TST4-MUC4-0047

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 27 OCT 88 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA TODAY RELEASED A PROVISIONAL REPORT ON THE DAMAGE CAUSED BY HURRICANE JOAN AND ANNOUNCED AN "IMMINENT CONTRA" ATTACK AGAINST NICARAGUA.

ACCOMPANIED BY FIVE FSLN NATIONAL DIRECTORATE COMMANDERS--HUMBERTO ORTEGA, BAYARDO ARCE, VICTOR TIRADO, CARLOS NUNEZ, AND TOMAS BORGE--AND MEMBERS OF HIS CABINET, ORTEGA ADDRESSED MEMBERS OF THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS ACCREDITED IN NICARAGUA AND THE FOREIGN PRESS TO REQUEST MORE INTERNATIONAL AID FOR THE NICARAGUANS AFFECTED BY HURRICANE JOAN.

ORTEGA ALSO ASKED THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY FOR ITS MEDIATION IN LIGHT OF A NEW ATTACK BY 3,000 "CONTRAS" WHO, ACCORDING TO ORTEGA, ARE AT THE HONDURAN BORDER READY TO LAUNCH AN ATTACK AGAINST HIS PEOPLE "IN THIS DIFFICULT TIME."

"THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY MUST DEMAND THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT FORGET ITS PLAN TO ATTACK NICARAGUA. THE CONTRAS HAVE BEEN EQUIPPED BY THE REAGAN ADMINISTRATION AND ARE READY TO ATTACK AT ANY MOMENT," THE NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT ADDED.

"WE KNOW THAT THE REBELS HAVE BEEN ORDERED TO HINDER THE RECONSTRUCTION WORK THAT IS BEING DONE TO HELP THE PEOPLE AFFECTED BY THE HURRICANE. THEY HAVE ALSO BEEN ORDERED TO SABOTAGE THE COFFEE HARVEST ACTIVITIES. THE BIGGEST HELP THE YANKEE GOVERNMENT COULD GIVE THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE WOULD BE TO STOP THE ATTACK," THE PRESIDENT STRESSED.

ORTEGA ANNOUNCED THAT WHILE HIS COUNTRY WAS BEING HIT BY HURRICANE JOAN, THE CONTRAS CARRIED OUT ATTACKS AND KILLED FIVE CIVILIANS.

REGARDING THE DAMAGE CAUSED BY THE HURRICANE, ORTEGA SAID THAT THIS COMING WEEK, AN ECLA TEAM WILL ARRIVE IN MANAGUA TO MAKE "FINAL" EVALUATIONS ON THE DAMAGE CAUSED BY JOAN LAST WEEK.

INTERNATIONAL AID "IS NECESSARY AND URGENT BECAUSE THE SITUATION IS CHAOTIC," ORTEGA ADDED, STRESSING THE ROLE PLAYED BY CUBA IN HELPING HIS PEOPLE.

HE SAID THAT CUBA SENT 24 PLANES TO NICARAGUA WITH FOOD, MEDICINE, AND MEDICAL TEAMS; MEXICO SENT 2 PLANES; AND SPAIN, GREAT BRITAIN, PANAMA, AND BELGIUM EACH SENT ONE; FOR A TOTAL OF 2,052 TONS OF AID.

GIVING A PROVISIONAL REPORT ON THE DAMAGE, ORTEGA SAID THERE WERE 116 DEAD, 178 INJURED, 110 MISSING, AND 29,152 HOUSES DESTROYED AS WELL AS DAMAGE TO AGRICULTURE AND FISHING.

HE STRESSED THE DAMAGE TO THE ECOLOGY BECAUSE THOUSANDS OF HECTARES OF FOREST WERE DESTROYED. HE SAID THAT EUROPEAN TECHNICIANS WILL TRAVEL TO NICARAGUA NEXT WEEK TO EVALUATE THE DAMAGE.

ORTEGA SAID THAT TO FACE THE HURRICANE, THE COUNTRY USED THE DEFENSE SYSTEM IT WOULD USE TO REPEL A MILITARY ATTACK AND THAT THANKS TO THIS, MANY HUMAN LIVES WERE SAVED.

TST4-MUC4-0048

BOGOTA, 29 OCT 88 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT ON NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS FOLLOWING CONCLUSION OF GROUP OF EIGHT MEETING IN PUNTA DEL ESTE, URUGUAY]

[TEXT] THE SECOND MEETING OF THE SO-CALLED GROUP OF EIGHT CONCLUDED TODAY IN PUNTA DEL ESTE, URUGUAY. AFTER THE URUGUAY DECLARATION WAS SIGNED, THE PRESIDENTS HOSTED A NEWS CONFERENCE. COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO ANSWERED A URUGUAYAN JOURNALIST'S QUESTION ON THE CURRENT SITUATION IN OUR COUNTRY:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] THE SITUATION IN YOUR COUNTRY IS VERY SERIOUS. THOUSANDS ARE DEAD, PARAMILITARY DEATH SQUADS GO UNPUNISHED DESPITE THEIR MURDERS OF PATRIOTIC UNION [UP] MEMBERS AND POPULARLY ELECTED LEGISLATORS. MR PRESIDENT, HOW CAN YOU EXPLAIN THIS SITUATION AND HOW CAN YOU RECONCILE THE SITUATION EXISTING IN YOUR COUNTRY WITH YOUR AFFIRMATION OF THE EXISTENCE OF DEMOCRACY? THANK YOU.

[BARCO] I DO NOT BELIEVE YOUR QUESTION IS RELEVANT TO THE COMPOSITION AND PURPOSE OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT MEETING. THE QUESTION ARISES FROM A LACK OF INFORMATION. COLOMBIA IS A DEMOCRACY, SUPPORTED BY A PROFESSIONAL ARMED FORCES. THE SOLDIERS ARE COLOMBIANS WHO ARE COMPLYING WITH THE REQUIREMENT TO PERFORM MILITARY SERVICE. THEY ARE YOUTHS FROM ALL GROUPS, FROM THE RURAL AREAS, THE CITIES, AND FROM ALL POLITICAL PARTIES. THE OFFICERS ARE PROFESSIONALS, AND THEY DO NOT FOLLOW MILITARIST DOCTRINES.

THE ARMED FORCES MEMBERS WHO HAVE PARTICIPATED--MAY I ADD ON AN INDIVIDUAL AND PERSONAL BASIS--IN ANY HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS ARE UNDER INVESTIGATION, WILL BE ARRAIGNED BEFORE A MILITARY COURT, AND MANY OF THEM HAVE BEEN EXPELLED. CIVIL COURTS HAVE BEEN NOTIFIED OF SOME OF THOSE CRIMES, AND SOME ARREST WARRANTS HAVE BEEN ISSUED. MILITARY JUSTICE AUTHORITIES ARE ALSO CONDUCTING LEGAL ACTIONS. [END RECORDING]

DURING THE SAME NEWS CONFERENCE THIS MORNING, PRESIDENT BARCO NOTIFIED JOURNALISTS THAT LAST THURSDAY'S STRIKE HAD BEEN AN ATTEMPT BY ARMED REBEL GROUPS AGAINST DEMOCRACY. HE ALSO SAID THAT THE PRESS CENSORSHIP DECREE WAS NO LONGER VALID.

TST4-MUC4-0049

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 88 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [REPORT] [ELMER GOMEZ] [TEXT] [GOMEZ] PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE CALLED ON THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL PARTIES THAT WILL PARTICIPATE IN THE UPCOMING ELECTIONS TO PROTECT THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS AND THE REPUBLIC. DUARTE MADE THIS CALL DURING HIS SPEECH OPENING THE 13TH INTERNATIONAL FAIR OF EL SALVADOR, IN WHICH 25 COUNTRIES ARE PARTICIPATING.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DUARTE] I HAVE ALWAYS BEEN A PEACE LOVER, AND THAT IS WHY IT GRIEVES ME TO SEE THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE CURRENT SALVADORAN CONFLICT AND CRISIS. I, HOWEVER, BELIEVE THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS WILL BE STRENGTHENED. I BELIEVE THE MINDS OF MEN WILL BE TRANSFORMED POSITIVELY, AND IDEOLOGICAL STRUGGLES--EVEN THE MOST POLARIZED ONES--WILL BE DEFINITELY SOLVED BY THE CIVILIZED MEANS OF THE ELECTORAL PROCESS.

I CALL ON ALL POLITICAL PARTIES TO STRENGTHEN THE CURRENT POLITICAL PROCESS AND PUT THE SACRED INTERESTS OF THE NATION BEFORE ANY OTHER INTERESTS BECAUSE THAT IS THE ONLY WAY TO PROTECT THE REPUBLIC AND CONSOLIDATE THE DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTION THAT BELONGS TO ALL SALVADORANS.

I ALSO WANT TO MAKE A CALL TO ALL GROUPS SO THE ELECTORAL PROCESS, WHICH WILL CULMINATE WITH THE ELECTION OF A NEW PRESIDENT NEXT YEAR, DEVELOPS WITH THE SPIRITUAL GRANDEUR THAT CORRESPONDS TO COURAGEOUS PEOPLE, WHO WISH TO SHOW THE WORLD THEIR POLITICAL MATURITY AND THEIR DESIRE TO LIVE IN PEACE.

THE ELECTORAL PROCESS WILL SLOWLY CONSOLIDATE. I BELIEVE SOONER THAN LATER, GOOD JUDGEMENT WILL PREVAIL IN THE MINDS OF THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN DRIVEN MAD BY BARBARISM. [END RECORDING]

[GOMEZ] PRESIDENT DUARTE ALSO SAID THE FMLN WILL NOT STOP THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS AND THAT THE SALVADORAN SITUATION IS DIFFERENT FROM THE ONE PRESENTED BY FMLN COMMANDERS JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS AND LEONEL GONZALEZ DURING THEIR LATIN AMERICAN TOUR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DUARTE] IT IS TRUE THAT THE ENEMIES OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WILL GO ON CONDUCTING THEIR TERRORIST AND DESTRUCTIVE ACTIONS. THOSE ACTIONS, HOWEVER, WILL NOT AT ALL AFFECT THE PROGRESS MADE BY OUR DEMOCRATIC STRUGGLE. THE TRUTH IS THAT OUR CRISIS IS AS LARGE AS THE EFFORT WE HAVE MADE TO FACE IT. THAT EFFORT GOES BEYOND OUR BORDERS AND REACHES THE ENTIRE WORLD.

THE SOCIAL AND POLITICAL CHANGES THAT BEGAN TO TAKE PLACE IN EL SALVADOR ARE [WORD INDISTINCT] AND HAVE BEGAN TO SHOW THEIR RESULTS, DESPITE THE DESPERATE ACTIONS THE FMLN-FDR IS CONDUCTING ABROAD IN ORDER TO COUNTER THE RESULTS OF THE PROGRESS WE HAVE MADE.

THE FOREIGNERS WHO CAME TO PARTICIPATE IN THIS FAIR AS WELL AS THE DISTINGUISHED OAS GENERAL ASSEMBLY DELEGATES WILL CONFIRM THAT THE SALVADORAN SITUATION IS VERY DIFFERENT FROM THAT CIRCULATED ABROAD AND DISSEMINATED AS PART OF AN FMLN -FDR DISINFORMATION PLAN.

THE REPRESENTATIVES OF OUR LOCAL SUBVERSIVE MOVEMENTS HAVE SAID ABROAD THAT THERE IS REPRESSION IN EL SALVADOR. ONLY A GOVERNMENT THAT IMPOSES ITSELF BY FORCE ON ITS PEOPLE CAN BE DESCRIBED AS A REPRESSIVE GOVERNMENT. OUR COUNTRY NEVER ENJOYED SO MUCH FREEDOM AS NOW AND ITS RULERS WERE NEVER CHOSEN SO FREELY AS THEY ARE NOW. [END RECORDING]

[GOMEZ] [WORD INDISTINCT] PRESIDENT DUARTE SAID THE 18TH OAS REGULAR MEETING REPRESENTS THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES' SUPPORT FOR THE SALVADORAN DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

TST4-MUC4-0050

BERLIN (FRG), 6 NOV 88 (ADN/ND) -- [TEXT] AT A NEWS CONFERENCE IN BERLIN ON FRIDAY [4 NOVEMBER], VOLODIA TEITELBOIM, MEMBER OF THE POLITICAL COMMISSION AND SECRETARIAT OF THE PCCH CENTRAL COMMITTEE, GAVE A REPORT ON THE SITUATION IN CHILE FOLLOWING THE REFERENDUM. HE SAID THAT THE PEOPLE'S RESOLUTE "NO" IN THE REFERENDUM ON 5 OCTOBER MUST NOW BE FOLLOWED BY THE OVERTHROW OF PINOCHET AND THE RETURN TO DEMOCRACY. THE FORMER SENATOR SAID THAT THE MOST URGENT CONDITION FOR THE PATH INTO THE FUTURE IS THE CREATION OF A BROAD UNITY OF ALL OPPOSITION FORCES WHICH CAN WIN A VICTORY OVER PINOCHET. HE SAID THAT THE COMMUNIST PARTY ALSO CONSIDERS COOPERATION, IN PARTICULAR WITH THE SOCIALISTS, A DECISIVE STEP.

HE SAID THAT QUITE A FEW THINGS HAVE CHANGED IN CHILE THROUGH THE BROAD MASS MOVEMENT. HIGH OFFICERS WHO SERVED THE DICTATOR MOST LOYALLY HAVE HAD TO RESIGN NOW UNDER PRESSURE FROM THE DEMOCRATIC PUBLIC. IN ADDITION, IT HAS JUST BEEN REPORTED THAT EL SIGLO, THE COMMUNIST PARTY NEWSPAPER, WILL BE PUBLISHED AGAIN LEGALLY.

ASKED ABOUT THE PRESENT CONDITIONS OF THE STRUGGLE, TEITELBOIM SAID THAT THE PROGRESSIVE FORCES IN CHILE, WHO HAD TO PAY A HIGH PRICE FOR THEIR RESISTANCE IN THE PINOCHET'S 15-YEAR RULE, CONTINUE TO BE EXPOSED TO PERSECUTION, IMPRISONMENT, AND THREATS OF MURDER. THE COMMUNIST PARTY, WHICH HAS HAD THE LARGEST NUMBER OF CASUALTIES AND MISSING AND TORTURED PEOPLE SINCE THE DICTATORSHIP WAS ESTABLISHED, CONTINUES TO BE BANNED.

NONETHELESS, THE COUNTRY IS CAUGHT UP IN A WAVE OF MOBILIZATION OF THE PEOPLE. VOLODIA TEITELBOIM CONFIRMED THAT THE COMMUNIST PARTY SUPPORTS THE DEMAND MADE BY THE OPPOSITION ALLIANCE TO HOLD THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS PROMISED BY THE MILITARY JUNTA FOR LATE 1989 AT AN EARLIER DATE, AND TO NOMINATE A COMMON PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE. IN ADDITION, THE CONSTITUTION--ON THE BASIS OF WHICH PINOCHET INTENDS TO CONTINUE IN OFFICE UNTIL MARCH 1990 DESPITE HIS DEFEAT THROUGH THE REFERENDUM--MUST BE ABOLISHED TO ALLOW THE PEOPLE TO DECIDE ON THE COUNTRY'S FUTURE IN FREEDOM.

VOLODIA TEITELBOIM PAID TRIBUTE TO THE GDR'S CONSISTENT POSITION IN WORD AND DEED AS A GREAT EXAMPLE OF INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY WITH THE CHILEAN PEOPLE. HE SAID THAT HUNDREDS OF PATRIOTS FROM HIS COUNTRY HAVE FOUND A TEMPORARY HOME IN THE GDR, WHERE THEY CAN LIVE AND WORK.

TST4-MUC4-0053

QUITO, 27 NOV 88 (VOZ DE LOS ANDES) -- [TEXT] GOVERNMENT MINISTER ANDRES VALLEJO YESTERDAY AGAIN DENIED THE CLAIM OF COMMANDERS JOAQUIN AND JAVIER OF THE ALFARO LIVES DAMMIT SUBVERSIVE GROUP THAT THEY HAVE MET WITH HIM. THE REBEL LEADERS MAINTAIN THEY HAVE MET ON FIVE OCCASIONS WITH THE GOVERNMENT WITHIN A FRAMEWORK OF CONSULTATIONS AND COORDINATION PROPOSED BY PRESIDENT RODRIGO BORJA. ACCORDING TO THEM, ONE OF THE MEETINGS INVOLVED MINISTER VALLEJO HIMSELF, WHO REPORTEDLY INTRODUCED THEM TO A DELEGATE OF PRESIDENT BORJA FOR FURTHER TALKS.

NEVERTHELESS, VALLEJO DID NOT RULE OUT THE POSSIBILITY OF HOLDING TALKS WITH THE GUERRILLAS TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN THE COUNTRY. FEBRES-CORDERO'S ADMINISTRATION REFUSED TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE ALFARO LIVES DAMMIT AND FREE HOMELAND MONTONERAS GUERRILLA GROUPS BECAUSE IT CONSIDERED THEM TO BE TERRORIST GROUPS; IT ACTUALLY ATTACKED THESE GROUPS TO THE POINT OF ALMOST ELIMINATING THEM.

VALLEJO POINTED OUT THAT HOLDING TALKS WITH THE GUERRILLAS WOULD BE A POSITIVE STEP. HE RECALLED THAT THE COLOMBIAN ADMINISTRATION OF BELISARIO BETANCUR BEGAN A DIALOGUE WITH GENUINE REVOLUTIONARY ARMIES TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN THAT COUNTRY. HE ASKED: WHY CAN WE NOT HOLD TALKS HERE, WHERE THE GUERRILLAS ARE STILL AT AN EMBRYONIC PHASE?

THE POSSIBILITY OF GOVERNMENT-GUERRILLAS TALKS HAS BEEN VIEWED DIFFERENTLY. NATIONAL CONGRESS PRESIDENT WILFRIDO LUCERO SAID ON 25 NOVEMBER THAT THE CONGRESS IS NEITHER TASKED NOR EMPOWERED TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE GUERRILLAS. LUCERO REFUSED TO COMMENT ON THE ALLEGED TALKS, SAYING THAT HE HAS RECEIVED NO INFORMATION IN THIS REGARD. HE ADDED: THESE KINDS OF PROBLEMS ARE UNDER THE JURISDICTION OF OTHERS; IT IS NOT A CONCERN OF THE NATIONAL CONGRESS.

ACCORDING TO JULIO CESAR TRUJILLO, A FORMER PRESIDENT OF POPULAR DEMOCRACY, TALKS WITH GUERRILLAS WOULD BE GOOD FOR THE COUNTRY BECAUSE THEY HAVE USEFUL IDEAS, SOME OF WHICH COULD BE IMPLEMENTED. HE ADDED THAT NOT EVERYTHING ADVOCATED BY THE GUERRILLAS CAN BE CARRIED OUT BECAUSE THERE ARE OBSTACLES FACING THE GOOD OFFICES OF THE CURRENT RULERS.

MEANWHILE, THE SOCIAL CHRISTIAN PARTY OF FORMER PRESIDENT LEON FEBRES-CORDERO EXPRESSED CONCERN OVER THIS POSSIBILITY. IT WILL MEET TOMORROW TO DISCUSS THE TOPIC AND ISSUE AN STATEMENT. MARCO LARA, PRESIDENT OF THAT PARTY AND PUBLIC INFORMATION SECRETARY DURING THE PREVIOUS ADMINISTRATION, REFUSED TO COMMENT ON THIS.

WHILE IN QUITO [AS HEARD], COMMANDERS JOAQUIN AND JAVIER ARE PROPOSING A BROAD AND DIRECT DIALOGUE WITH RODRIGO BORJA'S REGIME; IN GUAYAQUIL, LEADERS JUAN CUBIA AND EDGAR PRIAS, BOTH IN PRISON, AND PATRICIO BAQUERIZO ARE REJECTING A DEMAND THAT THE MOVEMENT RESPECT THE LAW.

TST4-MUC4-0056

BOGOTA, 28 NOV 88 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [MARIA CLARA GRACIA] [TEXT] IN VENEZUELA, AUTOPSIES HAVE BEEN PERFORMED ON 9 OF THE 14 FISHERMEN--INCLUDING 2 COLOMBIANS--KILLED IN EL AMPARO. THE AUTOPSY REPORTS ARE BEING WIDELY DISCUSSED. THE INVESTIGATIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT DIRECTLY INVOLVE THE MILITARY AUTHORITIES.

COLOMBIAN FOREIGN MINISTER JULIO LONDONO PAREDES HAS REQUESTED COORDINATED ACTIONS BY THE TWO COUNTRIES TO PREVENT SUCH BORDER INCIDENTS.

IT WAS ADMITTED THAT THE REMAINS OF THE FISHERMEN WERE EXHUMED OVER THE WEEKEND. SEVEN OF THEM WERE EXHUMED ON 26 NOVEMBER AND SIX ON 27 NOVEMBER IN VENEZUELA. THE JUDICIAL REPORT STATED THAT THERE WERE NO GUERRILLA CLASHES AND THAT EACH WAS KILLED BY A COUP DE GRACE OF THE VENEZUELAN ARMY.

THE VENEZUELAN INVESTIGATIVE COMMISSION ENTRUSTED WITH CLARIFYING THE VENEZUELAN MILITARY AUTHORITIES' REASONS FOR SLAUGHTERING 14 FISHERMEN ON 22 OCTOBER IN EL AMPARO DIRECTLY INVOLVE THE SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS.

THE AUTOPSIES PERFORMED ON NINE BODIES HAVE ESTABLISHED THAT THE PEASANTS OF THE BORDER AREA DID NOT HAVE AN ARMED CLASH WITH THE MILITARY. ON THE CONTRARY, THEY WERE SHOT AT A DISTANCE LESS THAN 1 METER, WHICH IS WHAT THE TWO SURVIVORS SAID FROM THE BEGINNING. THOSE SURVIVORS HAVE NOW REQUESTED ASYLUM IN CARACAS FROM THE MEXICAN GOVERNMENT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LONDONO] WE HOPE SUCH INCIDENTS WILL DECREASE AND THAT THE VENEZUELAN AUTHORITIES ALONG THE BORDER WILL COORDINATE WITH THE COLOMBIAN CIVILIAN AND MILITARY AUTHORITIES ANY ACTIONS FOR PRESERVING--NOT ONLY THE LIVES OF THE COLOMBIANS ON EITHER SIDE OF THE BORDER--PEACE AND TRANQUILLITY IN THE BORDER AREA. [END RECORDING]

BECAUSE 2 OF THE 14 MURDERED FISHERMEN WERE COLOMBIANS, LONDONO PAREDES STATED THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL MAINTAIN ITS INITIAL STAND OF DEMANDING COMPENSATION FOR THE RELATIVES OF THE DEAD COLOMBIANS. THE GOVERNMENT WILL ALSO AWAIT AN OFFICIAL NOTIFICATION FROM VENEZUELA ON THE RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS ON THE EL AMPARO SLAUGHTER.

TST4-MUC4-0057

SAN SALVADOR, 28 NOV 88 (TCS TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [ROBERTO REPRESA] [TEXT] COLONEL MAURICIO ERNESTO VARGAS, COMMANDER OF THE ARMY'S 3D BRIGADE IN SAN MIGUEL, HAS STATED THAT THE ARMED FORCES IS NOT INVOLVED IN DEATH SQUAD ACTIONS AND THAT SUCH ACTIONS ARE CONTRARY TO THE INSTITUTION'S REGULATIONS. VARGAS WAS REFERRING SPECIFICALLY TO THE MURDER OF THREE PEASANTS IN MORAZAN, OF WHICH THE ARMY IS BEING ACCUSED:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VARGAS] OUR VALUES AND THE VALUES OF THE SYSTEM WE DEFEND DO NOT ALLOW US TO EXECUTE, KIDNAP, OR STEAL. THE SYSTEM STATES WE ARE TO COMPLY WITH OUR LAWS AND LET THE RESPONSIBLE INSTITUTIONS DETERMINE GUILT OR INNOCENCE. WE CANNOT BE JUDGE AND JURY IN SUCH SITUATIONS. [END RECORDING]

THE MOST RECENT CASE FOR WHICH THE ARMY IS BEING BLAMED IS THE MURDER OF THREE PEASANTS IN YAMABAL CANTON, MORAZAN, ON 12 NOVEMBER. VARGAS DENIED ARMED FORCES COMPLICITY IN THESE MURDERS AND STATED THAT HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS MUST INVESTIGATE IN CASES OF THIS NATURE SO THEY CAN PRESENT EVIDENCE AND ACCUSE A SPECIFIC SECTOR. HE ADDED THAT HE HAS EVIDENCE THE ARMY WAS NOT PRESENT IN YAMABAL CANTON ON THE DAY OF THE TRIPLE MURDER:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VARGAS] I DIRECTLY ACCUSE THE FMLN AND TELL THE HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS THAT ARE ACCUSING THE ARMED FORCES TO INVESTIGATE THE FMLN. THE HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS MUST NOT ACCEPT DIALECTIC CONCLUSIONS SUCH AS THE ONES MADE BY THE CRIMINAL JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, WHO SAID WE EXECUTED AND [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THEY ARE NOT GOD. THEY TALK AS IF THE WORLD BELONGED TO THEM. THERE ARE LAWS AND A LEGAL FRAMEWORK IN THIS COUNTRY. OUR SYSTEM HAS A LEGAL FRAMEWORK, AND WE HAVE TO BASE OURSELVES ON IT. THERE ARE HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS THAT HAVE BECOME CORRUPT AND HAVE BECOME ACCOMPLICES OF THE FMLN'S MURDER; THEY REMAIN SILENT AND DO NOT DEFEND JUSTICE, LAWS, AND PRINCIPLES. REGARDING THIS CASE, I ACCUSE THE FMLN OF THESE DEATHS. WE HAVE EVIDENCE THE FMLN IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ACTS PRESENTLY BEING REPORTED IN THE NORTHWESTERN ZONE. [END RECORDING]

COL VARGAS ALSO CRITICIZED THE WORK DONE BY SOME HUMANITARIAN ORGNIZATIONS AND SAID THEY USE HUMAN RIGHTS AS AN EXCUSE TO PROTECT SECTORS THAT SHARE THEIR IDEOLOGY.

TST4-MUC4-0060

LIMA, 28 OCT 88 (EFE) -- [TEXT] EEC AND ANDEAN GROUP OFFICIALS HAVE HELD MEETINGS AT THE CARTAGENA AGREEMENT BOARD HEADQUARTERS TO PROGRAM ACTIVITIES AIMED AT INCREASING TRADE TIES BETWEEN THE TWO GROUPS.

ACCORDING TO WHAT THE CARTAGENA AGREEMENT BOARD, A TECHNICAL-COMMUNITY INTEGRATION ORGANIZATION, REPORTED TODAY, THE POLITICAL AGREEMENTS THAT WERE ADOPTED BY THE ANDEAN-EUROPEAN JOINT COMMISSION IN THE MEETINGS HELD IN BRUSSELS IN APRIL ARE NOW BEING IMPLEMENTED THROUGH THE HOLDING OF THESE TALKS.

THE FIRST MEETING IN LIMA WILL BE TO DISCUSS FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES SUCH AS THE BETTER USE OF THE GENERALIZED PREFERENTIAL RATES SYSTEM THAT IS IMPLEMENTED BY THE EEC, THE ESTABLISHMENT OF ACTIVITIES TO PROMOTE TRADE, AND THE DEVELOPMENT OF ANDEAN EXPORTS.

THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THESE AGREEMENTS NOT ONLY ENCOMPASS THE STRENGTHENING OF TRADE TIES, BUT ALSO INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT AND ECONOMIC COOPERATION FOR DEVELOPMENT.

PETER HEISLER, THE CHIEF OF THE EEC DELEGATION, SAID THAT THIS MEETING SHOWS "OUR WILLINGNESS TO COOPERATE."

ACCORDING TO STATISTICS PROVIDED BY THE CARTAGENA AGREEMENT BOARD, IN 1986 THE ANDEAN GROUP, COMPRISED OF BOLIVIA, ECUADOR, COLOMBIA, PERU, AND VENEZUELA, RECORDED A DEFICIT OF $266 MILLION IN ITS TRADE WITH EEC COUNTRIES.

THIS DEFICIT IN ANDEAN TRADE, WHICH HAS NOT BEEN RECORDED SINCE 1982, WHEN THE FOREIGN DEBT CRISIS EXPLODED IN ANDEAN GROUP COUNTRIES, IS CAUSED BY THE FALL BY ALMOST 23 PERCENT OF ANDEAN EXPORTS, WHICH IN 1988 TOTALED $3.847 BILLION.

THIS DEFICIT IS ALSO CAUSED BY AN INCREASE OF 18 PERCENT IN ANDEAN IMPORTS FROM EEC COUNTRIES, WORTH $4.113 BILLION.

BETWEEN 1970 AND 1986, THE ANDEAN GROUP ACCUMULATED A TRADE DEFICIT OF $2.175 BILLION WITH THE GROUP OF 12.

DURING THIS PERIOD, ANDEAN EXPORTS TOTALED $54.795 BILLION, WHILE IMPORTS TOTALED $56.970 BILLION.

THE COOPERATION AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CARTAGENA AGREEMENT BOARD MEMBERS AND EEC COUNTRIES WAS SIGNED ON 17 DECEMBER 1983 IN CARTAGENA, COLOMBIA.

LATER, THE CONGRESSES OF ALL THE COUNTRIES COMPRISING THE ANDEAN GROUP APPROVED THE AGREEMENT WHILE NEGOTIATIONS TO IMPLEMENT THEM, PARTICULARLY REGARDING TRADE, HAVE BEEN TAKING PLACE SINCE APRIL 1988.

TST4-MUC4-0061

SAN SALVADOR, 2 NOV 88 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [MAGDALENA JIMENEZ] [EXCERPTS] AT LEAST TWO PEOPLE WERE KILLED AND FOUR WERE WOUNDED EARLY THIS MORNING DURING AN FMLN ATTACK ON THE EL ANGEL SUGAR MILL LOCATED NEAR APOPA.

THE GUERRILLA ACTION BEGAN AT APPROXIMATELY MIDNIGHT WHEN ABOUT 50 GUERRILLAS ARMED WITH RIFLES AND MORTARS ATTACKED THE SUGAR MILL, WHICH IS LOCATED 15 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR. DURING THE ATTACK, THE GUERRILLAS PARTIALLY DESTROYED THE ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICES OF THE SUGAR MILL AND A NEARBY HOUSE. THE SUGAR PROCESSING EQUIPMENT AND MACHINERY WERE NOT DAMAGED. AFTER ABOUT AN HOUR, THE INSURGENTS WITHDREW. THE NUMBER OF FMLN CASUALTIES IS UNKNOWN. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

AT THE SAME TIME THAT THIS ATTACK WAS TAKING PLACE, THE FMLN STAGED HARASSMENT ATTACKS ON 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE UNITS GUARDING THE LAS CANAS BRIDGE, WHICH IS LOCATED ON THE ROAD FROM APOPA TO QUEZALTEPEQUE. IT HAS BEEN UNOFFICIALLY REPORTED THAT THE ARMY SUFFERED TWO DEAD AND TWO WOUNDED IN THIS ATTACK, BUT THIS REPORT WAS DENIED BY THE ARMED FORCES.

THE TWO ACTIONS ARE PART OF A NEW FMLN MILITARY MANEUVER THAT BEGAN YESTERDAY WITH THE ATTACK ON THE NATIONAL GUARD HEADQUARTERS, WHERE 4 GUARDSMEN WERE KILLED AND 30 WOUNDED.

TST4-MUC4-0064

SAN SALVADOR, 4 NOV 88 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [INTERVIEW WITH NATIONAL POLICE DIRECTOR COLONEL CARLOS MAURICIO GUZMAN AGUILAR AT NATIONAL POLICE HEADQUARTERS, SAN SALVADOR, BY AN UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [EXCERPTS] [BEGIN RECORDING] [GUZMAN] I HAVE BEEN WORKING JOINTLY WITH THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF--NOT JUST THIS WEEK BUT FOR SEVERAL MONTHS. I HAVE TO ADD THAT NOT ONLY THE NATIONAL POLICE ARE INVOLVED, BUT THE PUBLIC SECURITY FORCES AND THE MILITARY CORPS STATIONED HERE IN SAN SALVADOR. WE HAVE REINFORCEMENTS FROM THE COUNTRYSIDE AND ARE WORKING ON A JOINT PLAN TO HELP MINIMIZE TERRORIST ATTACKS THAT THEY WILL TRY TO CARRY OUT AND ARE CARRYING OUT AT THIS VERY MOMENT.

JUST TO GIVE YOU AN EXAMPLE, RIGHT NOW WE ARE WAITING FOR A DEMONSTRATION THAT IS TO BEGIN AT THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY. THERE WILL BE STUDENTS TOGETHER WITH UNTS [NATIONAL UNION OF SALVADORAN WORKERS] MEMBERS, WHO ARE GOING TO MARCH THEIR USUAL ROUTE AND END UP AT THE PARK ACROSS FROM THE CATHEDRAL.

I WANT TO TELL YOU THAT THEY ARE NOT GOING TO HAVE ANY PROBLEMS AS LONG AS THEY OBEY THE LAW. AS I SAID A FEW DAYS AGO, WE DO NOT WANT CONFRONTATIONS WITH ANYONE. WHAT THEY WANT IS TO CONFRONT POLICE AND PUBLIC SECURITY FORCES FOR THE SAKE OF CREATING A MARTYR, AND WE ARE UNWILLING TO OBLIGE THEM IN THIS ENDEAVOR. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

[REPORTER] THE ATTACK AGAINST THE NATIONAL GUARD SEEMS LIKE A CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE SECURITY CORPS. WE WOULD LIKE TO KNOW IF THE NATIONAL POLICE ARE ON ALERT FOR AN ATTACK IN VIEW OF THE ATTACKS AGAINST THE NATIONAL GUARD AND THE TREASURY POLICE?

[GUZMAN] AS I SAID BEFORE, THIS IS NOT NEW FOR US, AND WE ARE MAKING PLANS. YOU NOTICE THAT THE GENERAL HEADQUARTERS IS CLOSE TO HOMES. WE HAVE ALREADY SEEN IN USULUTAN AND IN SAN FRANCISCO MORAZAN WHERE THESE PEOPLE ATTACKED WITHOUT CARING WHETHER THEY DESTROYED PRIVATE PROPERTY OR HOMES--EVEN KILLING INNOCENT CIVILIANS. WE ARE NOT EXEMPT FROM THIS HERE. WE HAVE A STRATEGY. WE EVEN BELIEVE THERE IS A POSSIBILITY OF AN ATTACK FROM INSIDE THE GENERAL HEADQUARTERS--IT IS VERY POSSIBLE, THEY HAVE DONE IT BEFORE. I REMEMBER WHEN THEY BOMBED THE SERVICE STATION HERE, DESTROYING THREE OR FOUR VEHICLES, AND THEY ALSO PLACED BOMBS INSIDE THE GENERAL DIRECTORATE OFFICE. WE ARE DOING ALL WE CAN TO TRY TO AVOID THESE PROBLEMS. WE ARE READY TO FACE ANY SITUATION. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

[REPORTER] WHAT PLANS HAVE YOU MADE FOR THE UPCOMING OAS GENERAL MEETING, AND WHAT SECURITY RESPONSIBILITIES WILL THE NATIONAL POLICE HAVE IN REGARD TO THIS MEETING?

[GUZMAN] YOU MUST UNDERSTAND THESE ARE MAINLY MILITARY PLANS WHICH WE CANNOT VERY WELL DISCLOSE IN ADVANCE. IF I STARTED GIVING OUT THIS INFORMATION, I WOULD BE EXPOSING OUR SECURITY OPERATION FOR THE MEETING. ALL I CAN SAY IS THAT WE ARE TAKING THIS SITUATION VERY SERIOUSLY. WE HAVE REINFORCEMENTS FROM THE COUNTRYSIDE. NOT ONLY IS THE NATIONAL POLICE INVOLVED, BUT THE PUBLIC SECURITY CORPS, AS WELL AS OTHER UNITS THAT HAVE COME FROM THE COUNTRYSIDE TO SUPPORT THIS COMMON EFFORT. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

TST4-MUC4-0065

TEMUCO, 4 NOV 88 (SANTIAGO RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [TEXT] THE FIVE INDIVIDUALS WHO WERE DETAINED IN THE MOUNTAINOUS REGION OF COCOAN AND ARE ACCUSED OF BELONGING TO THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT [FPMR] TERRORIST ORGANIZATION ARE BEING HELD INCOMMUNICADO AT THE SOCIAL REHABILITATION CENTER.

THE MILITARY PROSECUTOR OF CAUTIN, RODOLFO CALSEN, HAS 5 DAYS, BEGINNING TODAY, TO BRING CHARGES AGAINST THEM, AND TO EITHER CONDEMN OR RELEASE THEM FOR LACK OF EVIDENCE.

THE DETAINEES, AS PREVIOUSLY REPORTED, HAVE BEEN IDENTIFIED AS MAXIMILIANO RIVERA, 31; ALDO ESTEBAN MUTARELO, 30; AND A WOMAN IDENTIFIED AS ANGELICA HUERTA HUERTA, 26. THEY WERE ALL DETAINED IN THE CATRIPULLI SECTOR, SOME 30 KM FROM PUCON, TOWARD THE MOUNTAINS. TWO M-16 RIFLES WERE FOUND ON THESE INDIVIDUALS, ALONG WITH AMMUNITION, EXPLOSIVES, AND SUBVERSIVE MATERIAL.

TWO OTHER PEOPLE WERE LATER ARRESTED. THEY WERE IDENTIFIED AS ADOLFO MAS STILMAN FLORES, 29, AND ARNALDO RIVERA. NO WEAPONS WERE FOUND ON THEM.

THESE DETAINTIONS WERE CARRIED OUT LAST MONDAY, 31 OCTOBER, BUT THE REPORT WAS RELEASED TO THE COMMUNICATIONS MEDIA ONLY YESTERDAY AFTERNOON [3 NOV]. THE DETAINEES ARE REPORTEDLY BEING HELD INCOMMUNICADO WHILE AWAITING A RESOLUTION. IF THE DEADLINE IS NOT EXTENDED, WE WILL HAVE SOME NEWS TOMORROW ON WHETHER THEY WILL BE SUBMITTED TO TRIAL OR BE ACQUITTED FOR LACK OF EVIDENCE.

TST4-MUC4-0069

SAN SALVADOR, 9 NOV 88 (TCS TELEVISION) -- [INTERVIEW WITH DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL CARLOS VIDES CASANOVA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS]

[EXCERPTS] [REPORTER] DEAR LISTENERS, THE MINISTER HAS ARRIVED AND WE WELCOME HIM AND THANK HIM FOR HIS PARTICIPATION IN THIS SEGMENT. GOOD MORNING.

[VIDES] GOOD MORNING.

[REPORTER] VIOLENCE HAS INCREASED RECENTLY AND THE PEOPLE ARE EXTREMELY WORRIED. WHAT ARE THE ARMED FORCES DOING TO GUARANTEE THE PEOPLE'S WELFARE?

[VIDES] THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S CONCERN ABOUT INCREASED TERRORIST VIOLENCE IS UNDERSTANDABLE. WE MUST BEAR IN MIND THAT TERRORIST ACTS ALWAYS ESCALATE WHEN IMPORTANT EVENTS ARE EXPECTED. THIS DOES NOT HAPPEN ONLY IN OUR COUNTRY; WE RECENTLY SAW IT IN SEOUL, BEFORE THE OLYMPICS, WHEN GROUPS RESORTED TO VIOLENCE TO PROVOKE THE AUTHORITIES AND PREVENT AN INTERNATIONAL EVENT FROM TAKING PLACE.

AN OAS MEETING IS SCHEDULED TO TAKE PLACE IN THIS COUNTRY IN A FEW DAYS. THE EVENT IS BEING THREATENED BY A NUMBER OF ACTS, PARTICULARLY TERRORIST ACTS IN THE SAN BENITO, MAX DIAZ, ESCALON, AND SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOODS. THE TERRORISTS BELIEVE THE PEOPLE WILL PROTEST AGAINST THE OAS MEETING IF THEY CAUSE TERROR IN THOSE AREAS.

WE ARE EXPECTING FOREIGN MINISTERS FROM LATIN AMERICA, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE UNITED STATES, WHOM THE TERRORISTS BELIEVE WILL CALL OFF THE MEETING BECAUSE OF THE SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY. THAT IS THE MAIN REASON FOR THE INCREASED VIOLENCE.

YOU HAVE SEEN THAT WE HAVE INCREASED PATROL OPERATIONS RECENTLY. PATROLS ARE ALSO BEING CARRIED OUT AROUND THE VOLCANOES NEAR SAN SALVADOR. SECURITY MEASURES ARE ALSO BEING IMPLEMENTED ON THE PERIPHERY OF SAN SALVADOR AND AROUND THE MEETING VENUE, BUT I CANNOT GIVE YOU THE DETAILS. THERE IS ALSO A COMPLETE SECURITY PLAN FOR THE OFFICIALS WHO WILL PARTICIPATE IN THE OAS MEETING.

WE ARE READY TO REDUCE THE POSSIBILITY OF AN INCIDENT TO A MINIMUM. HOWEVER, I HAVE ALWAYS BEEN HONEST AND I MUST ADMIT THERE IS ALWAYS THE POSSIBILITY OF SABOTAGE OR A TERRORIST ACT. THIS DOES NOT NECESSARILY MEAN THAT IT WILL AFFECT THE SECURITY MEASURES IN THE AREA OF THE MEETING. FOR EXAMPLE, A BLACKOUT CAN BE CAUSED BY CUTTING OFF AN ELECTRIC LINE IN A DISTANT AREA.

[REPORTER] GENERAL, THE FMLN'S ATTACKS HAVE NOT BEEN SO OVERWHELMING IN THE PAST, YET NOW THOSE ATTACKS ARE ATTAINING CONSIDERABLE MILITARY SUCCESS. DO THE FMLN'S MILITARY ACTIONS MEAN IT IS SUPERIOR TO THE ARMED FORCES?

[VIDES] WE CANNOT CONCEIVE THEIR MILITARY SUPERIORITY UNDER ANY CIRCUMSTANCES. I HAVE NOTICED THE GUERRILLA LEADERS ARE CURRENTLY VISITING DIFFERENT COUNTRIES, PARTICULARLY THE CONTADORA GROUP MEMBERS. THEY ARE TRYING TO GAIN SUPPORT FOR READING A STATEMENT AT THE OAS MEETING, AND THEY ARE ALSO TRYING TO PRESSURE THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT INTO NEGOTIATING WITH THEM. THIS PROVES THE REBELS HAVE FAILED MILITARILY, AND THAT FAILURE HAS BEEN BROUGHT ABOUT BY OUR LARGE-SCALE OPERATIONS IN NORTHERN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT AND USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, IN THE EAST OF THE COUNTRY.

THE REBELS HAVE TRIED TO BRING THE WAR TO URBAN AREAS. HOWEVER, THE PLANS OF SUBVERSIVE GROUPS--I SHOWED YOU THE DOCUMENTS ON THEIR FIRE PLAN IN ANOTHER MEETING--DID NOT INCLUDE THE TYPE OF TERRORIST ACTS THAT WE HAVE SEEN LATELY. INSTEAD, THEY PLANNED A GENERAL UPRISING AND STRIKE BEFORE THE ELECTIONS.

THIS PROVES, AS I SAID, THAT THE SUBVERSIVES COULD NOT DEVELOP THEIR FIRE PLAN. THEY HAVE CARRIED OUT SEVERAL ACTS BUT THEY HAVE FAILED TO ACHIEVE THE EXPECTED RESULTS. THIS IS LIKE HAVING A CINEMA SHOW A MOVIE EVERY DAY WITH NO-ONE TURNING UP TO SEE IT.

THE SUBVERSIVES ARE TRYING TO CARRY OUT THIS TYPE OF EVENT RIGHT NOW TO GIVE THE IMPRESSION OF MILITARY STRENGTH, SO THE OAS WILL PASS A RESOLUTION RECOMMENDING NEGOTIATION TO SOLVE THE CONFLICT.

FURTHERMORE, THE REBELS ARE TRYING TO DISCREDIT THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS AND BOYCOTT OUR NEXT ELECTIONS BECAUSE SOME PEOPLE ARE DEMORALIZED BY TERRORISM AND LACK THE WILL TO PARTICIPATE IN POLITICS, WHICH MAKES THE ELECTION RESULTS UNSATISFACTORY. [CONTINUED]

TST4-MUC4-0070

LIMA, 10 NOV 88 (EFE) -- [TEXT] LEGISLATIVE SOURCES REPORTED IN LIMA TODAY THAT THE PERUVIAN CONGRESS HAS APPROVED A BILL ESTABLISHING MORE SEVERE PENALTIES FOR TERRORISTS AND ALSO ESTABLISHING PUNISHMENTS FOR THE SUPPORT OF TERRORIST ACTS.

THE BILL, WHICH WAS DISCUSSED IN THE CHAMBER OF DEPUTIES AND THE SENATE, ESTABLISHES PRISON TERMS RANGING FROM 10 TO 20 YEARS. IT WAS IMMEDIATELY SENT TO THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH FOR PROMULGATION.

THE BILL WAS APPROVED 3 MONTHS AFTER PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA PRESENTED IT TO CONGRESS ON 28 JULY, WHEN GARCIA COMPLETED THE 3D YEAR OF A 5-YEAR TERM OF OFFICE WHICH BEGAN IN 1985.

THE PROVISIONS APPROVED BY CONGRESS AMEND 6 ARTICLES IN SECTION 8, VOLUME 2 OF THE PERUVIAN PENAL CODE, ADDING MORE SEVERE SENTENCES AND THE MEANS FOR EXPANDING COURT ACTIONS AGAINST SUBVERSION.

A PRISON TERM OF 20 YEARS OR MORE WILL BE IMPOSED ON THOSE WHO CAUSE ANXIETY, ALARM, OR TERROR AMONG THE POPULATION OR ANY PART OF IT, ACTS AGAINST A PERSON'S LIFE OR HEALTH, OR ACTS AGAINST PRIVATE OR PUBLIC PROPERTY IF SUCH ACTS IMPAIR THE COMMUNITY'S BASIC SERVICES.

IN ALL CASES, THE INSTIGATORS OR MASTERMINDS, THE PRINCIPALS IN THE SECOND DEGREE, AND THE ACCOMPLICES WILL RECEIVE THE SAME SENTENCES AS THE PERPETRATORS.

MORE SEVERE SENTENCES HAVE ALSO BEEN ESTABLISHED FOR CASES IN WHICH A PERPETRATOR BELONGS TO AN ORGANIZATION THAT USES TERRORISM AS A MEANS TO ACHIEVE ITS GOALS, INCLUDING THE MAOIST "SHINING PATH" ORGANIZATION AND THE MRTA.

SUPPORTING, APPROVING, OR PRAISING TERRORIST ACTS CAN BE PUNISHED WITH PRISON TERMS OF 5 YEARS OR MORE, AND A 5-YEAR PRISON TERM HAS BEEN ESTABLISHED FOR THE CRIME OF MAKING, PURCHASING, STEALING, OR STORING WEAPONS OR EXPLOSIVES FOR THE PURPOSE OF TERRORISM.

MORE THAN 12,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KILLED IN PERU IN SUBVERSIVE AND ANTI-SUBVERSIVE ACTIONS SINCE THE "SHINING PATH" ORGANIZATION BEGAN ITS ARMED STRUGGLE IN 1980. MORE THAN $10 BILLION IN MATERIAL LOSSES HAVE BEEN REGISTERED AS WELL.

TST4-MUC4-0071

BOGOTA, 17 NOV 88 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [RAUL GUTIERREZ] [TEXT] A NEW DIPLOMATIC RIFT HAS ARISEN BETWEEN COLOMBIA AND THE NEIGHBORING REPUBLIC OF VENEZUELA FOLLOWING A PROTEST NOTE SENT BY OUR FOREIGN MINISTRY TO THE VENEZUELAN FOREIGN MINISTRY. THE NOTE DENOUNCES THE MASSACRE OF 14 FISHERMEN, INCLUDING TWO COLOMBIANS WHOM THE VENEZUELAN ARMED FORCES ACCUSED OF BEING SUBVERSIVES.

THE VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT DECIDED THAT IT WOULD NOT BE SCOLDED BY COLOMBIA, SO THE VENEZUELAN FOREIGN MINISTRY SENT A NOTE TO OUR FOREIGN MINISTRY WHICH SAID THAT VENEZUELA REJECTED THE TERMS USED IN THE COLOMBIAN PROTEST NOTE.

COLOMBIA HAS SENT 17 FOREIGN MINISTRY NOTES TO VENEZUELA IN THE PAST 2 YEARS, ALL CONCERNING INCIDENTS THAT HAVE DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY AFFECTED COLOMBIAN CITIZENS. ONLY 2 OF THE 17 PROTEST NOTES HAVE RECEIVED A REPLY, AND THEY NEVER INCLUDED THE RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS REQUESTED BY OUR GOVERNMENT.

THE LAST NOTE REPRESENTS A PROTEST FROM OUR GOVERNMENT FOR THE MURDER OF JOSE ANTONIO AREGUA AND JUSTO PASTOR CEBALLOS ON 29 OCTOBER. THEY WERE ASSASSINATED ALONG WITH 12 VENEZUELAN CITIZENS WHEN THE VENEZUELAN ARMY MISTOOK THEM FOR NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY REBELS IN CANO COLORADA, ARAUCA DEPARTMENT, ALONG THE VENEZUELAN BORDER.

EVEN THOUGH THERE IS EVIDENCE THAT THE VENEZUELAN AUTHORITIES MADE A MISTAKE, THE COUNTRY'S REPLY TO THE NOTE WAS SPITEFUL AND UNSATISFACTORY. THIS REPRESENTS THE WORST DIPLOMATIC INCIDENT BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES SO FAR THIS YEAR.

ILDEGAR PEREZ, VENEZUELAN AMBASSADOR TO COLOMBIA, PERSONALLY REFERRED TO THE STATE OF RELATIONS BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PEREZ] LET US SAY THAT RELATIONS AT THIS POINT ARE DELICATE, BUT I WOULD NOT CHARACTERIZE THEM AS CRITICAL OR EXTREMELY DIFFICULT. [END RECORDING]

THE VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT HAS ORDERED THAT THE TWO SURVIVORS OF THE 29 OCTOBER MASSACRE AT THE BORDER BE TRIED. MOREOVER, THE DISPUTE BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES IS BEING EXPLOITED IN THE VENEZUELAN PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN. VERY FEW, HOWEVER, DARE TO SPEAK THE TRUTH ABOUT THE SITUATION.

[VENEZUELAN DEPUTY JUVENCIO PULGAR] [BEGIN RECORDING] WE HAVE DISPUTES AND WE SHOULD NOT COVER THEM UP. COLOMBIA AND VENEZUELA HAVE THINGS TO PROTEST ABOUT, BUT ONLY A DIALOGUE WILL LEAD TO AN AGREEMENT TO SETTLE THESE DISPUTES. [END RECORDING]

TST4-MUC4-0073

SANTIAGO, 24 OCT 88 (ANALISIS) -- [ARTICLE] [NELSON SOZA MONTIEL] [TEXT] [CONTINUED]

THE INFLATION `BOGEYMAN'

THIS ENTIRE PANORAMA CHANGED WITH THE NO VOTE VICTORY. AND WITH IT CHANGED THE POLICIES AND TOOLS THAT BUCHI'S TEAM WILL HAVE TO RESORT TO UNTIL LATE 1989 AND THAT ARE NOW MUCH MORE DEPENDENT THAN BEFORE ON THE GOVERNMENT'S POLITICAL OBJECTIVES. ONE OPTION IS TO KEEP ON DOING "MORE OF THE SAME," TO IGNORE THE NEW CONTEXT THAT HAS DEVELOPED SINCE 5 OCTOBER, TO DEFUSE THE MONETARY TIME BOMB AND TO APPLY A TIGHT TOURNIQUET TO THE ECONOMY TO PREVENT RENEWED OUTBREAKS OF HIGHER PRICES.

THE INFLATION "BOGEYMAN" IS BEGINNING TO MAKE HIS PRESENCE FELT (THE CONSUMER PRICE INDEX, CPI, IS EXPECTED TO BE UP 1.3 TO 1.5 PERCENT THIS MONTH), AND EXPLANATIONS ABOUND. GERARDO ACEITUNO, THE HEAD OF THE FORECASTING WORKSHOP OF THE LABOR ECONOMY PROGRAM, ATTRIBUTES THE MOUNTING INFLATIONARY PRESSURES TO THE IMPACT OF THE WAGE HIKE AND HIGHER INTERNATIONAL INTEREST RATES ON DOMESTIC PRICES. HE RECALLS THAT THE PRICES OF FARM PRODUCTS HAVE BEEN "VIRTUALLY FROZEN FOR A YEAR" AND THAT THIS EXPLAINS THE HUGE GAP BETWEEN THE WHOLESALE PRICE INDEX, WHICH FELL ONE PERCENT DURING THE PAST 12 MONTHS, AND THE CPI, WHICH ROSE 12 PERCENT DURING THE SAME PERIOD. "THE SITUATION COULD NOT BE SUSTAINED, EXCEPT IF BUSINESSMEN WANTED TO SACRIFICE THEIR PROFIT MARGINS, WHICH HAVE SO FAR NOT BEEN AFFECTED, BECAUSE THE VAT WAS CUT."

JUAN VILLARZU, IN CONTRAST, PLACES MOST OF THE BLAME FOR THE INFLATIONARY PRESSURES ON THE EXCESSIVE QUANTITY OF MONEY. ODDLY ENOUGH, HOWEVER, THE UNCERTAINTY THAT DEVELOPED AFTER THE VICTORY OF THE NO VOTE IS PRESUMABLY HAVING AN EFFECT SOMEWHAT SIMILAR TO THE "MINI-ADJUSTMENT." HE REPORTS THAT SMALL- AND MEDIUM-SIZED BUSINESSMEN ARE POSTPONING THEIR INVESTMENT PLANS, AND THUS THEIR DEMAND FOR CREDIT HAS FALLEN OFF. THE DILEMMA FACING THEM AND OTHER "ECONOMIC AGENTS" IS WHETHER TO SPEND THE MONEY OR TO DEPOSIT IT. THE CENTRAL BANK COMES INTO PLAY HERE, BECAUSE "NOT HAVING TO COMPETE WITH THE BANKS, IT CAN BEGIN SOAKING UP SOME OF THE MONEY IN CIRCULATION WITHOUT BOOSTING INTEREST RATES TOO MUCH. MOREOVER, THEY ARE ALREADY QUITE HIGH: 5 PERCENT FOR 90-DAY OPERATIONS, AS AGAINST 4.2 PERCENT DURING THE FIRST HALF." IN ADDITION, IT COULD RESORT TO ITS SIZABLE MONETARY RESERVES AND "BURN UP" FOREIGN EXCHANGE ON HIGHER IMPORTS TO ABSORB SOME OF THE EXCESS LIQUIDITY. "I'M THINKING ABOUT DEVALUATIONS (OF THE PESO) SOMEWHAT SIMILAR TO THE ONES THIS YEAR."

OPTIONS AFTER THE NO VICTORY

IN ANY EVENT, THE LARGE MASS OF MONEY IN CIRCULATION AND THE EXISTING INFLATIONARY PRESSURES (WHATEVER THEIR CAUSE) "CONSTITUTE AN EXPLOSIVE SITUATION," WHICH ACCORDING TO VILLARZU THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT IGNORE. BECAUSE "IF IT HAS ANY POLITICAL ACCOMPLISHMENT LEFT, IT IS THE VICTORY OVER INFLATION." AND THE TIGHTENING UP WILL BE EVEN MORE SEVERE IF THE FINANCE MINISTER INSISTS ON ACHIEVING A 5-PERCENT RISE IN THE CPI IN 1989, AS THE DRAFT BUDGET SENT TO THE JUNTA CALLS FOR. EVEN THE CENTRAL BANK REGARDS THIS GOAL AS DANGEROUS. A HIGH-LEVEL CENTRAL BANK EXECUTIVE SAID THAT "IT IS VALID TO AIM FOR AN INFLATION RATE LIKE THAT IN THE DEVELOPED COUNTRIES, BUT WE HAVE TO BE CAREFUL BECAUSE UNEMPLOYMENT (WHICH WOULD TRIGGER A HEAVY CONCENTRATION OF SPENDING) REMAINS HIGH."

ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THE GOVERNMENT'S ECONOMIC CARD ARE THE ALREADY VISIBLE AND STRONG PRESSURES THAT THE RIGHT HAS BEGUN TO APPLY SO THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL INCREASE SPENDING IN 1989 OR AT LEAST NOT REDUCE IT. THE RIGHT ALSO WANTS THE GOVERNMENT TO TAKE ACTIONS THAT ARE MORE POPULIST IN NATURE OR THAT HAVE LESS VISIBLE EFFECTS ON VOTERS. SIGNIFICANTLY, EXPERTS ON BUCHI'S OWN TEAM ARE THE ONES WHO ARE ADMITTING THAT POLITICAL DEMANDS CAN BE GIVEN TO SOME EXTENT WITHOUT IGNORING CERTAIN PRINCIPLES. GAINING GROUND, AS A RESULT, ARE AN INCREASE IN THE MINIMUM WAGE ("TO PAVE THE WAY FOR HIGHER PAY IN PRIVATE ENTERPRISE") AND FURTHER CUTS IN THE VAT (THE RUMOR OF A CUT TO 12 PERCENT WAS ALREADY MAKING THE ROUNDS BEFORE THE PLEBISCITE) AND IN THE TAX ON CAPITAL. BUT THE PRIVATIZATION OF ENTERPRISES IS STILL STRONGLY SUPPORTED AS WELL. EVERYTHING POINTS IN THE SAME DIRECTION: "REDUCE THE SIZE OF THE PUBLIC AND GOVERNMENT SECTOR AND, AT THE SAME TIME, NARROW THE MANEUVERING ROOM ON TAXES FOR A GOVERNMENT DIFFERENT FROM THIS ONE." IF IT IS SIMILAR, SO MUCH THE BETTER. [CONTINUED]

TST4-MUC4-0074

BOGOTA, 3 NOV 88 (EL TIEMPO) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED]

THE GUERRILLAS TURN TERRORIST

THE PRESIDENT OF PATRIOTIC UNION, BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA, FEELS THAT THE SANCTION IMPOSED ON THE TWO URABA UNIONS LAST WEEK WAS UNFAIR BECAUSE HE BELIEVES THAT THE STRUGGLE OF THE WORKERS HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH THE PHENOMENON OF VIOLENCE IN THE ZONE.

JARAMILLO ACKNOWLEDGED, HOWEVER, THAT THE GUERRILLA GROUPS IN URABA HAVE SHIFTED FROM SUBVERSION TO ABSURD ACTS OF TERRORISM AND VANDALISM THAT CANNOT BE COMPARED TO ACTS ANYWHERE ELSE IN THE COUNTRY.

THE LEFTIST LEADER DESCRIBED THIS TERRORIST ESCALADE AS ONE OF THE MAJOR OBSTACLES TO THE REGION'S ACHIEVING THE SOCIAL PACT THAT IT URGENTLY NEEDS.

THE CONGRESSMAN FELT THAT THE SHUTDOWN OF THE UNIONS HAS DEPRIVED THEM OF SPOKESMEN AND HE RECALLED THAT URABA HAS ACHIEVED ITS WEALTH THROUGH PRIVATE ENTERPRISE, WITHOUT THE SLIGHTEST GOVERNMENT INVOLVEMENT.

MORE SELF-CRITICISM

SENATOR ALBERTO ROJAS PUYO, ONE OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION CONGRESSMEN, CONTENDED YESTERDAY THAT THE RESIGNATION OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE CUT, JORGE CARRILLO, OUGHT TO HELP PROMPT THE LEFT TO MAKE A SERIES OF RECTIFICATIONS.

ROJAS SAID: "JORGE CARRILLO'S LETTER OF RESIGNATION AS PRESIDENT OF THE CUT CONTAINS VERY IMPORTANT PROPOSALS NOT ONLY FOR THE ORGANIZATION BUT ALSO FOR ALL DEMOCRATIC FORCES. I AM GLAD THAT HIS RESIGNATION WAS NOT ACCEPTED AND I SEE IN THIS DEVELOPMENT THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE FORCES OF THE LEFT WILL BEGIN A SERIOUS PROCESS OF REFLECTION AND NECESSARY RECTIFICATION SO THAT THEIR STRUGGLES ARE UNDERSTOOD AND TAKEN UP BY THE WORKING CLASS AND THE PEOPLE AT LARGE.

"SOME OF CARRILLO'S PROPOSALS ARE, WITHOUT DOUBT, DEBATABLE, BUT THE INDISCRIMINATE MIX OF ACTIONS IS UNQUESTIONABLY DOING GREAT DAMAGE TO THE COUNTRY AND, MOST OF ALL, TO THE LEFT. A CLEAR LINE MUST BE DRAWN IN WORD AND IN DEED WITH RESPECT TO VIOLENCE. THE FACT THAT SUCH CRUCIAL ASPECTS FOR COLOMBIA'S DEMOCRATIC DEVELOPMENT WERE DEBATED WITHIN A MAJOR LABOR FEDERATION SHOWS THAT THIS CLASS CAN PLAY A GUIDING ROLE FOR THE PEOPLE AT LARGE.

"THE IMPORTANT THING IS THAT ALONG WITH THE NECESSARY REFORMS, THE UNITY OF THE FEDERATION AND ITS CAPACITY FOR ALLIANCES AND GRASSROOTS MOBILIZATION EMERGE STRENGTHENED."

TST4-MUC4-0075

SAN SALVADOR, 28 NOV 88 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [JOEL BURGOS] [TEXT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE [CHAIRMAN OF THE SALVADORAN JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF] APPEARED BEFORE THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY TODAY. THE ASSEMBLY OFFERED TO LOOSEN LEGAL [WORD INDISTINCT] ON THE ARMED FORCES TO WIN THE WAR.

SOME GROUPS BELIEVE THE COUNTRY ENTERED A CRISIS WITH THE 15 OCTOBER 1979 MILITARY COUP. SINCE THEN, EL SALVADOR HAS SUFFERED A CIVIL WAR THAT IS GETTING WORSE AND CAUSING MORE CASUALTIES. THERE ARE NOW TWO DISTURBING CHANGES IN THE WAR: FIRST, CORPSES ARE BEING DUMPED ON THE ROADSIDE, WHICH REMINDS US OF THE EARLY 1980'S WHEN DEATH SQUADS WERE ACTIVE. SECOND, URBAN GUERRILLA ACTIVITY IS INCREASING. THE ARMED FORCES ARE JUSTIFIABLY CONCERNED ABOUT THOSE ISSUES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] I NEVER TALK ABOUT DEATH SQUADS. I TALK ABOUT VIOLENCE AND THE ACTIONS OF THE RIGHT- AND LEFT-WING GROUPS. THE ARMY IS DETERMINED, AND IS MAKING ALL THE NECESSARY EFFORTS, TO COUNTER THOSE VIOLENT ACTIONS, REGARDLESS OF WHICH GROUPS CARRY THEM OUT. [END RECORDING]

COL PONCE MET WITH MEMBERS OF THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY COMMITTEE TODAY.

AFTER 8 YEARS, THE WAR SEEMS TO BE ENDLESS. ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] BELIEVES THAT A SOLUTION TO THE CRISIS COULD BE THE FORMATION OF A COMMON FRONT THAT WILL SET UP A NATIONAL STRATEGY AND ALSO LOOSEN LEGAL RESTRICTIONS ON THE ARMED FORCES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ARENA DEPUTY SIGIFREDO OCHOA] WE MUST SET UP A NATIONAL STRATEGY, BECAUSE WE CANNOT LET THE GUERRILLAS KILL US. I THINK THAT WE MUST ACT WITHIN THE LAW. I THINK WE MUST LOOSEN THE LEGAL RESTRICTIONS ON THE ARMY, BECAUSE THE ARMY CAN BE EFFECTIVE BUT HAS ITS HANDS TIED. [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN ITS OWN COUNTRY, IT HAS BEEN REJECTED FOR HAVING DEFENDED COMMUNIST GUERRILLAS [WORDS INDISTINCT], WHICH IN [WORD INDISTINCT] ITSELF IS CONSIDERED AS [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE CANNOT UNDERSTAND HOW CAN IT DEFEND A CRIMINAL POSITION. IT IS TIME FOR US TO RALLY AROUND A SINGLE PURPOSE. [END RECORDING]

THERE CAN STILL BE A PEACEFUL SOLUTION TO THE CRISIS. CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC] PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE FIDEL CHAVEZ MENA SAID HE WILL SEEK A DIALOGUE WITH THE GUERRILLA MOVEMENT. MEANWHILE, ARENA WILL MAKE ITS OWN PROPOSAL TO THE FMLN.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [OCHOA] THE PDC PROMISED TO ACHIEVE PEACE. THAT IS AN ILLUSION. THAT IS WHAT THE PDC CANDIDATE IS PROPOSING. CHAVEZ MENA HAS BEEN IN THE GOVERNMENT FOR YEARS, AND THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT CHANGE ITS STRATEGY. THAT PROPOSAL IS MERELY A SMOKESCREEN.

WE HAVE BEEN VERY CLEAR ABOUT THIS. WE MUST SIT DOWN TO TALK WITH THE REBELS WITHIN A STRICT TIME LIMIT AND WITHOUT SO MUCH DEMAGOGY. WE ARE WILLING TO TALK WITH THE FMLN-FDR. WE WANT TO MAKE A PROPOSAL TO THEM--NOT AN ARENA PROPOSAL, BUT A NATIONAL PROPOSAL. [END RECORDING]

TST4-MUC4-0076

BOGOTA, 5 DEC 88 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SENATOR ALVARO LEYVA DURAN BY MARIA CLARA GRACIA, IN PROGRESS] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [LEYVA] ...OVER THE RED TELEPHONE AND SECOND, ALL HOSTILITIES HAVE UNILATERALLY ENDED ON ALL FARC FRONTS. THE GOVERNMENT ONCE ASKED ME WHY THEY DO NOT BEGIN A UNILATERAL END OF HOSTILITIES IF THEY HAVE GOODWILL. HERE IT IS. I CANNOT DO ANY MORE; I HOPE THE GOVERNMENT DOES NOT LET THIS OPPORTUNITY PASS.

[GRACIA] DO YOU BELIEVE TALKS SHOULD CONTINUE WITH THE GUERRILLA GROUPS?

[LEYVA] THE TRUTH IS THAT I PROPOSED SOMETHING TO THE GOVERNMENT, THE POLITICAL PARTIES, AND THE GUERRILLAS. WHAT YOU CALL TALKS IS NOTHING MORE THAN THE GUERRILLAS' REPLY TO THE PROPOSAL--THE SAME WAY AS [FORMER PRESIDENT] DR TURBAY, SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE PARTY PRESIDENT DR FABIO VALENCIA, AND DR JARAMILLO OSSA OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION DID. THE CARDINALS HAVE BEEN INFORMED OF THE PROPOSAL, AND THE M-19 AND FARC HAVE REPLIED. IN FACT, THEY WENT EVEN FURTHER; THEY UNILATERALLY ENDED HOSTILITIES. NOW THE BALL IS IN THE GOVERNMENT'S COURT.

[GRACIA] TAKING INTO ACCOUNT THAT AFTER AGREEING NOT TO, FOR EXAMPLE, CARRY OUT ANY AMBUSHES AGAINST TROOPS, THE GUERRILLAS CONTINUED; THEY BROKE THE AGREEMENT. DO YOU THINK WE CAN AGAIN TRUST THESE STATEMENTS?

[LEYVA] I CANNOT MEASURE THE CONFIDENCE THAT SHOULD BE GIVEN TO OTHERS. THE ONLY THING I KNOW IS THE GOVERNMENT IS SEEKING PEACE, SO I IMAGINE THIS IS PRECISELY THE WAY. THE SUSPICION THAT THE GOVERNMENT MIGHT HAVE OF THEM IS THE SAME AS YOU MIGHT HAVE, BUT IF THE GOVERNMENT SEEKS PEACE, HERE IS WHERE THEY CAN FIND IT, WITH A PRELIMINARY END TO HOSTILITIES ON ALL FRONTS. THIS IS WHAT [FARC GENERAL SECRETARY] JACOBO ARENAS WROTE IN A LETTER THAT WAS NOT ADDRESSED TO ME BUT TO THE FORMER PRESIDENTS OF COLOMBIA. [END RECORDING]

TST4-MUC4-0077

LIMA, 2 DEC 88 (EFE) -- [TEXT] PRESUMED SHINING PATH MAOIST EXTREMISTS AMBUSHED AND KILLED 68 PEASANTS IN THE LOCALITY OF BALCON, 200 KM NORTH OF THE SOUTHERN CITY OF AYACUCHO.

A PEASANT DEFENSE PATROL UNIT WAS COMBING THE AREA IN SEARCH OF GUERRILLAS WHEN IT WAS AMBUSHED ON 22 NOVEMBER, THE NEWSPAPER EXPRESO REPORTED TODAY.

THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE HAS HIT PERUVIAN TOURIST ESTABLISHMENTS IN THE CITY OF HUARAZ, CAPITAL OF THE ANCASH DEPARTMENT, WHERE FOUR INNS AND HOTELS WERE BOMBED LAST NIGHT, DAMAGING THE BUILDINGS AND INJURING AN 18 YEAR-OLD GIRL.

IN CUSCO, 1,000 KM SOUTHEAST OF LIMA, A BUS [AS RECEIVED] HEADING TOWARD MACHU PICHU WENT OUT OF CONTROL AS THE RESULT OF SABOTAGE AND FELL INTO A 60-METER RAVINE. THE WIVES OF THE JERSEY CITY, UNITED STATES, AND CUSCO MAYORS DIED IN THIS ACCIDENT.

LEFTIST SENATOR ENRIQUE BERNALES BALLESTEROS, PRESIDENT OF THE SPECIAL COMMISSION FOR THE INVESTIGATION AND STUDY OF TERRORISM AND VIOLENCE, HAS NOTED THAT THE ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE HAS CLAIMED THE LIVES OF 21 PEOPLE PER DAY DURING THE MONTH OF NOVEMBER. HE SAID THAT THE INCREASED VIOLENCE CAN BE TRACED TO ACTIONS BY THE TERRORIST GROUPS SHINING PATH AND TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA). THESE ATTACKS WERE REPRESSED BY THE FORCES OF ORDER.

SENATOR BERNALES REPORTED THAT 630 PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN VIOLENT ACTS IN NOVEMBER AND THAT 1,775 HAVE BEEN KILLED OVER THE PAST 12 MONTHS.

BERNALES SAID THAT 403 PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN NOVEMBER AS A RESULT OF VIOLENT ACTS, INCLUDING 147 CIVILIANS, 165 PRESUMED TERRORISTS, 65 ARMED FORCES MEMBERS, AND 26 DRUG TRAFFICKERS. A TOTAL OF 227 PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN URBAN VIOLENT ACTS.

SENATOR BERNALES ADDED THAT A TOTAL OF NEARLY 13,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KILLED SINCE THE TERRORIST VIOLENCE BEGAN IN 1980.

BERNALES EXPRESSED HIS CONCERN OVER THE FACT THAT 67 PERCENT OF THE PEOPLE KILLED IN VIOLENT ACTS INVOLVED YOUTHS WHO WERE BETWEEN 15 AND 29 YEARS OF AGE. HE ASKED THE GOVERNMENT TO ESTABLISH GUIDELINES TO COUNTER THIS SOCIAL PHENOMENON.

AMID THIS BLOODY AND DESTRUCTIVE SITUATION, THE PERUVIAN EPISCOPAL CONFERENCE HAS MADE A CHRISTMAS APPEAL, ASKING THAT--WITHOUT IGNORING "THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE SITUATION"--FOR A TRUCE "FOR PEACE, RECONCILIATION, AND TRANQUILLITY" TO PREVAIL IN THE COUNTRY.

THE BISHOPS SAID: "RECALLING HE WHO PREVAILED OVER DEATH, WE CALL UPON THOSE WHO HAVE RESORTED TO VIOLENCE AND KILLINGS AS A SOLUTION TO THE EVILS OF SOCIETY, TO ALLOW THE CITIZENS FOR WHOM THEY CLAIM TO STRUGGLE TO LIVE LIKE BROTHERS."

TST4-MUC4-0078

SAN SALVADOR, 5 DEC 88 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] THE ARMY HAS REPORTED THAT IT INFLICTED 208 GUERRILLA CASUALTIES DURING CLASHES IN NOVEMBER. MEANWHILE, THE FMLN REBELS HAVE SAID THEY INFLICTED 991 CASUALTIES ON THE ARMY--INCLUDING DEAD AND WOUNDED--AS A RESULT OF THEIR ATTACKS, HARASSMENT, AND AMBUSHES DURING THE SAME PERIOD.

THE MILITARY REPORT SAYS 93 FMLN GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED AND 115 WOUNDED AS A RESULT OF NATIONWIDE COUNTERINSURGENCY MILITARY OPERATIONS DURING THE MONTH OF NOVEMBER.

THE REPORT ADDED THAT DURING THE SAME PERIOD, THE ARMY CONFISCATED 105 HIGH-CALIBER RIFLES, 2 M-60 MACHINEGUNS, 20 REVOLVERS OF VARIOUS CALIBERS, MORE THAN 55,000 CARTRIDGES, 168 FRAGMENTATION GRENADES, 236 MINES, 9 COMMUNICATION RADIOS, AND A LARGE AMOUNT OF MATERIAL FOR HOMEMADE BOMBS.

THE MILITARY REPORT ADDED THAT DURING THE MONTH OF NOVEMBER, GUERRILLAS KILLED 43 PEASANTS, KIDNAPPED 32, AND CAUSED THE DEATH OF 6 PEOPLE AND CRIPPLED 23 OTHERS AS A RESULT OF MINE EXPLOSIONS.

IN THE WAR AGAINST PUBLIC PROPERTY--THE PILLAR OF A WAR ECONOMY--THE MILITARY SOURCE REPORTED THAT SIX MAYORIAL OFFICES AND SIX NATIONAL ADMINISTRATION FOR TELECOMMUNICATIONS OFFICES WERE DAMAGED IN VARIOUS TOWNS AND SIX JUNCTION BOXES WERE SABOTAGED.

IN ADDITION, 4 TRAINS BELONGING TO THE SALVADORAN NATIONAL RAILROAD, FENADESAL, WERE BLOWN UP, AND 10 VEHICLES AND 5 BUSES WERE PARTIALLY DAMAGED.

REGARDING DAMAGE TO THE ELECTRICITY SYSTEM, THE FMLN KNOCKED DOWN 46 TOWERS AND 136 HIGH-TENSION POWER POLES AND DAMAGED 11 TRANSFORMERS.

TST4-MUC4-0079

HAVANA, 3 DEC 88 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FRANCISCO VILLAGRAN, MEMBER OF THE URNG POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC COMMISSION, BY PEDRO MARTINEZ] [TEXT] [MARTINEZ] THERE IS A SUBJECT OF INTEREST TO RADIO HAVANA LISTENERS: THE URNG'S HUMANIZATION OF THE WAR POLICY.

[VILLAGRAN] RIGHT NOW, THE POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC COMMISSION, ON DIRECTIONS FROM THE URNG GENERAL COMMAND, IS MAKING EVERY EFFORT TO HUMANIZE THE WAR SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY, ESPECIALLY BY SHOWING RESPECT FOR THE GENEVA AGREEMENT, WHICH GUATEMALA SIGNED.

WE ARE DOING THIS BECAUSE THE REPRESSIVE WAR THE ARMY HAS BEEN WAGING AGAINST THE REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT AND THE POPULATION HAS REACHED LEVELS OF EXTREME CRUELTY, INCLUDING INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS AND THE USE OF DEFOLIANTS IN CONFLICT ZONES WHERE CIVILIANS LIVE.

THERE IS THE PARTICULAR SITUATION IN WHICH NEITHER THE GUATEMALAN ARMY NOR THE GOVERNMENT TAKE ANY WAR PRISONERS. THIS MAKES US BELIEVE THAT THE CRUELTY USED AGAINST CIVILIANS AND PEOPLE INVOLVED IN THE ARMED CONFLICT IS A VIOLATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS.

[MARTINEZ] DOES THE URNG HAVE ANY PRISONERS AT THIS MOMENT?

[VILLAGRAN] YES. WE HAVE SENT A NOTE TO THE NATIONAL RECONCILIATION COMMISSION SO IT CAN HANDLE THE CASE OF SOLDIER CARLOS PEREZ LOPEZ, WHO WAS CAPTURED WOUNDED IN THE SAN MARCOS REGION, NEAR GALVEZ. HE HAS BEEN GIVEN MUCH MEDICAL ATTENTION. NOW THAT HE HAS FULLY RECOVERED, WE ARE THINKING ABOUT PUBLICLY RETURNING THIS GUATEMALAN, AND WE ARE ASKING THE RECONCILIATION COMMISSION TO TAKE MEASURES THROUGH THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS [IRC] TO RECEIVE THIS MAN IN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE HUMANIZATION PROCESS.

[MARTINEZ] WILL THIS BE THE FIRST TIME THE URNG WILL MAKE THIS KIND OF CONTACT WITH THE IRC?

[VILLAGRAN] THE IRC HAS HAD LOCALIZATION PROBLEMS. THERE HAS BEEN THE ARGUMENT THAT THERE IS A NATIONAL RED CROSS. CONTACT WITH THE IRC IS POSSIBLE IF THERE IS A PRESENCE OF THIS ORGANIZATION THAT FUNCTIONS BASED ON INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENTS. NOW THAT THE IRC IS PRESENT, THE WORK IS BEING FACILITATED.

THE CONTACT WITH THE IRC IS AT THE INITIATION LEVEL. HOWEVER, I BELIEVE THESE CONTACTS WILL BE VERY USEFUL IN THE FUTURE, ESPECIALLY FOR PERSONS NOT INVOLVED IN THE ARMED CONFLICT.

[MARTINEZ] I THINK IT WOULD BE USEFUL IF WE CLOSE THIS INTERVIEW WITH YOU REPEATING THE NAME OF THE GUATEMALAN ARMY SOLDIER WHO IS BEING HELD BY THE URNG AND WHOM THE GUERRILLA FORCES ARE PREPARED TO TURN OVER TO THE IRC.

[VILLAGRAN] YES. HIS NAME IS CARLOS LOPEZ PEREZ [AS HEARD].

[MARTINEZ] THANK YOU, VILLAGRAN.

TST4-MUC4-0080

BOGOTA, 15 NOV 88 (SEMANA) -- [EXCERPTS] [PASSAGE OMITTED] IT WAS BARELY NOON WHEN A MAN WHO HAD JUST ARRIVED ON A FLIGHT FROM MEDELLIN WENT INTO THE NATIONAL BOOKSTORE TO BUY SOME NEWSPAPERS. MEANWHILE, HIS BODYGUARD-CHAUFFEUR WAITED FOR HIM IN THE LOBBY. THE MAN WITH THE NEWSPAPERS, A CATTLEMAN NAMED GUSTAVO DE JESUS ESCOBAR FERNANDEZ, HAD JUST LEFT THE BOOKSTORE WHEN THE TROUBLE STARTED. ESCOBAR WAS PREPARING TO GO TO HIS CAR WHEN A MAN APPROACHED HIM. THE MAN, AROUND 35 YEARS OLD AND 5 FEET 9 INCHES TALL, TOOK OUT A 7.65 CALIBER PISTOL AND BEGAN FIRING. PANIC SPREAD THROUGHOUT THE TERMINAL AS PEOPLE THREW THEMSELVES ON THE FLOOR TO AVOID BEING SHOT.

ESCOBAR IMMEDIATELY FELL TO THE FLOOR AS HIS ATTACKER TRIED TO ESCAPE THROUGH ONE OF THE EXITS. APPARENTLY, HE DID NOT TAKE INTO ACCOUNT THE PRESENCE OF THE BODYGUARD, WHO HAD ENOUGH TIME TO DRAW HIS GUN AND SHOOT THE AGGRESSOR, WHO DIED AT THE SCENE. ESCOBAR FERNANDEZ WAS TAKEN TO THE SAN PEDRO CLAVER CLINIC, WHERE HE WAS PRONOUNCED DEAD ON ARRIVAL. BUT THE TRAGIC EVENT DID NOT END THERE. A 20-YEAR-OLD WOMAN WHO WAS AT THE AIRPORT, MARIA FLOREZ GUTIERREZ, WAS SERIOUSLY WOUNDED AND HER CONDITION WAS LISTED AS SERIOUS WHEN THIS EDITION WENT TO PRINT.

EARLY DETAILS DID NOT CLARIFY THE MOTIVATION FOR THE ATTACK. ACCORDING TO DOCUMENTS FOUND IN HIS CLOTHING, IN ADDITION TO HIS ACTIVITIES AS A CATTLEMAN, GUSTAVO DE JESUS ESCOBAR WAS A LEGAL ADVISOR IN CONGRESS, ALTHOUGH THIS WAS DENIED BY SPOKESMEN FROM THAT INSTITUTION. THINGS TOOK ANOTHER TURN THAT EVENING, WHEN THE TELEVISION NEWS PROGRAM 24 HOURS REPORTED THAT ESCOBAR FERNANDEZ WAS THE COUSIN OF PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA. THIS GAVE RISE TO THE SUPPOSITION THAT THE ATTACK WAS LINKED TO THE SERIES OF KILLINGS IN THE SO-CALLED "CARTEL WAR."

AS TO THE ATTACKER, NEITHER HIS REAL MOTIVES NOR HIS IDENTITY WERE KNOWN AT THE END OF THE WEEK. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

TST4-MUC4-0084

BOGOTA, 10 DEC 88 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT ACCEPT MEDIATORS IN A DIALOGUE WITH THE GUERRILLAS, PRESIDENTIAL ADVISER RAFAEL PARDO RUEDA HAS SAID. THE OFFICIAL ADDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT CANNOT GUARANTEE THE SAFETY OF THE POLITICIANS OR GUERRILLAS WHO ATTEND THE REGIONAL TALKS WHICH ARE TAKING PLACE IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

THE PRESIDENTIAL ADVISER ALSO WARNED THAT THE GOVERNMENT WOULD NOT CHANGE ITS ATTITUDE TOWARD THE REBELS AND THAT ANY MEETINGS IN SEARCH OF PEACE WILL ONLY TAKE PLACE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLA LEADERS. EVEN THOUGH THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT RESPONDED TO SENATOR ALVARO LEIVA'S PROPOSAL, WHICH CALLS FOR A TOP-LEVEL COMMISSION TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE GUERRILLAS, THE FARC AND THE M-19 GUERRILLAS HAVE ALREADY ANNOUNCED THAT IF THE GOVERNMENT CALLS FOR THE CREATION OF SUCH A COMMISSION, THEY WOULD IMMEDIATELY ORDER A TRUCE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PARDO] THE GOVERNMENT CANNOT ASSUME THAT RESPONSIBILITY WITH PRIVATE INDIVIDUALS. OUR PEACE INITIATIVE CALLS FOR A DIRECT DIALOGUE WITH GUERRILLAS WHO ARE COMMITTED TO A RECONCILIATION, ONCE THE RIGHT CONDITIONS ARE PRESENT. THIS POSITION REMAINS UNCHANGED.

[REPORTER] DOES THIS MEAN SENATOR ALVARO LEIVA'S PROPOSAL HAS NOT BEEN TAKEN INTO ACCOUNT?

[PARDO] NO, THE GOVERNMENT WILL RESPOND TO DR LEIVA'S PROPOSAL IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS. HIS PROPOSAL HAS BROUGHT ABOUT POSITIVE RESULTS IN THE SENSE THAT THE FARC AND M-19 HAVE EXPRESSED THEIR DESIRE TO SUSPEND TERRORIST ACTS. THE GOVERNMENT WILL ANNOUNCE A FORMAL RESPONSE TO THIS PROPOSAL IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS. [END RECORDING]

MEANWHILE, FORMER PRESIDENTS BELISARIO BETHANCOURT AND MISAEL PASTRANA BORRERO URGED THAT A COMMISSION BE FORMED FOR TALKS WITH THE REBELS, WHICH THEY CONSIDER THE BEST CHANCE FOR PEACE.

TST4-MUC4-0085

LIMA, 10 DEC 88 (EFE) -- [TEXT] WITH THE MURDER OF TWO MORE ENGINEERS LAST WEDNESDAY, 7 DECEMBER--WHICH WAS LEARNED ABOUT ONLY TODAY IN LIMA--A TOTAL OF SIX ENGINEERS HAVE BEEN MURDERED THIS WEEK APPARENTLY BY MEMBERS OF THE MAOIST SHINING PATH GUERRILLA MOVEMENT. FOUR ENGINEERS, INCLUDING TWO FRENCHMEN, WERE MURDERED LAST SUNDAY.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS, A GROUP OF TERRORISTS LAST WEDNESDAY ENTERED THE LOCALITY OF SITUCANCHA, JUNIN DEPARTMENT, IN THE CENTRAL MOUNTAIN REGION OF PERU, AND GATHERED ALL THE PEOPLE AT THE MAIN SQUARE. THEY FORCED ADOLFO SPEZUA AND AUGUSTO VILCAHUMAN OUT OF THEIR OFFICES AND, AFTER A "PEOPLE'S TRIAL," SHOT THEM TO DEATH.

LAST SUNDAY, TERRORISTS MURDERED FOUR ENGINEERS--TWO PERUVIANS AND TWO FRENCHMEN--WHO WERE WORKING IN AN AGRICULTURAL DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM IN THE SMALL TOWN OF AQUIRA, IN THE SOUTHERN DEPARTMENT OF APURIMAC, WHERE SHINING PATH TERRORIST ACTIVITY IS INTENSE.

THE FRENCH ENGINEERS WERE IDENTIFIED AS THOMAS PELLISSIER AND CORINE SEGUIN. THE JUSTICE OF THE PEACE FROM AQUIRA WAS ALSO MURDERED.

MOREOVER, FIVE TERRORISTS AND AN ARMY CORPORAL WERE KILLED IN A CLASH BETWEEN TERRORISTS AND AN ARMY PATROL NEAR THE LOCALITY OF NANSHUIMPUQUIO, 41 KM FROM THE SOUTHERN CITY OF AYACUCHO.

NOVEMBER WAS A PARTICULARLY BLOODY MONTH BECAUSE OF THE POLITICAL VIOLENCE THAT CAUSED THE DEATH OF 403 PEOPLE. THIRTEEN THOUSAND PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KILLED BY SHINING PATH SINCE THE BEGINNING OF ITS ACTIVITIES IN 1980.

TST4-MUC4-0086

SAN SALVADOR, 14 DEC 88 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] IT WAS OFFICIALLY ANNOUNCED TODAY THAT MAYOR HECTOR AREVALO OF THE RULING CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC], WHO WAS ELECTED MAYOR IN A TOWN IN SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT LAST MARCH, RESIGNED BECAUSE OF DEATH THREATS FROM SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS.

AREVALO IS THE FIRST MAYOR TO RESIGN AS A RESULT OF FMLN THREATS. THE FMLN CLAIMS MAYORS ARE PART OF THE COUNTERINSURGENCY PLAN CONDUCTED BY THE SALVADORAN ARMY.

AREVALO, 39, WAS REPORTEDLY THREATENED WITH DEATH BY THE GUERRILLAS, WHO ALSO ORDERED HIM TO LEAVE THE TOWN OF SANTA CLARA, 65 KM EAST OF SAN SALVADOR.

AFTER ANNOUNCING HIS RESIGNATION, AREVALO SAID: "I WANT TO LIVE AND TO FEEL UNTAINTED. I DO NOT WANT TO HAVE ENEMIES. I HAVE A WIFE AND CHILDREN WHO NEED ME." AREVALO SAID, HOWEVER, THAT HE CANNOT LEAVE SANTA CLARA, A TOWN OF APPROXIMATELY 10,000 PEOPLE, BECAUSE HE CANNOT AFFORD TO DO SO.

THE FMLN ALSO CLAIMS THAT IN MANY TOWNS IN NORTHERN AND EASTERN EL SALVADOR, AN AREA OVER WHICH IT CLAIMS TO HAVE MORE CONTROL THAN THE ARMY, THERE ARE TWO POWER CENTERS: ONE IS THE GUERRILLA MOVEMENT, AND THE OTHER IS THE GOVERNMENT. THE FMLN HAS STATED THAT IT WILL NOT ALLOW THE GOVERNMENT TO CONTROL THAT REGION.

THUS FAR THIS YEAR, THE FMLN HAS KILLED EIGHT PDC AND RIGHTIST NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE MAYORS IN SANTA ANA, MORAZAN, SAN MIGUEL, AND USULUTAN DEPARTMENTS.

THE CATHOLIC CHURCH AND THE SALVADORAN POLITICAL PARTIES HAVE CONDEMNED THE MURDER OF THESE GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS.

TST4-MUC4-0088

LIMA, 14 DEC 88 (EFE) -- [TEXT] FOUR ALLEGED TERRORISTS, ALL WEARING SKI MASKS, MURDERED MAYOR ALFREDO CHAMORRO IN THE SMALL TOWN OF PALLANCHACRA. CHAMORRO WAS A MEMBER OF THE GOVERNING APRA.

THIS INFORMATION WAS RELEASED IN LIMA TODAY. THE ATTACK WAS PERPETRATED AT DAWN ON TUESDAY, 13 DECEMBER, WHEN THE TERRORISTS BURST INTO THE MAYOR'S HOME. CHAMORRO HAD PREVIOUSLY RECEIVED DEATH THREATS.

PALLANCHACRA IS LOCATED SOME 30 KM FROM CERRO DE PASCO, CAPITAL OF PASCO DEPARTMENT, IN CENTRAL PERU.

MOREOVER, ONE OF THE BODYGUARDS OF HUGO GARCIA SALVATECCI, BANK AND INSURANCE SUPERINTENDANT, IS RECOVERING IN A CLINIC IN LIMA FROM AN ATTACK BY ALLEGED TERRORISTS WHO SHOT HIM AS A "WARNING."

IN OTHER EVENTS, POLICE HAVE IDENTIFIED THE BODY OF A MAN FOUND LAST SATURDAY, 10 DECEMBER, ON KILOMETER 12 OF THE SOUTH PANAMERICAN HIGHWAY. HE WAS APPARENTLY SHOT.

THE INDIVIDUAL WAS IDENTIFIED AS AN ALLEGED MEMBER OF THE PERUVIAN COMMUNIST PARTY, WITH ENTRIES IN POLICE RECORDS.

A POSTER WHICH READ "AN EYE FOR AN EYE. FOR WHAT THE WORKERS REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT [MOR] IN BOLIVIA DID," WAS FOUND ON THE BODY.

THE AUTHORS OF THE CRIME WERE PRESUMABLY REFERRING TO THE MURDER IN LA PAZ, BOLIVIA, OF PERUVIAN NAVAL ATTACHE JUAN CARLOS VEGA LLONA. THE SELF-STYLED MOR CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE KILLING.

TST4-MUC4-0089

SANTIAGO, 10 NOV 88 (QUE PASA) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED]

VARYING INTENTIONS

THE PROGRAM FOR LEGAL ACTION CERTAINLY RAISES DIFFERENT EXPECTATIONS AMONG THE PARTNERS IN IU. THERE HAS BEEN TALK ABOUT THAT IN RECENT DAYS. ALL INDICATIONS ARE, INDEED, THAT BECAUSE TIME IS RUNNING SHORT THEY WILL START UP WITHOUT MUCH CIRCUMSPECTION. TO PUT IT MORE CLEARLY, THE PRESUMPTION IS THAT THEY WILL WAIT UNTIL THINGS ARE UNDER WAY BEFORE TRYING TO PUT THEIR OWN MARK ON THE NEWBORN.

CHRISTIAN LEFT [IC] WAS THE FIRST TO GIVE THIS SIGNAL. THE RESOLUTIONS OF ITS PLENUM, MADE PUBLIC ON 28 OCTOBER, CLEARLY REVEALED THAT IT INTENDED TO UNIFY THE ENTIRE LEFT IN THE FORMATION OF THE NEW POLITICAL ENTITY. IN PASSING, THEY SENT A MESSAGE TO THEIR MEN WHO WERE INVOLVED IN THE PPD [PARTY FOR DEMOCRACY]: THEY HAVE TO DECIDE BETWEEN MEMBERSHIP IN ONE OR THE OTHER, BUT NOT BOTH. THIS IS SOMETHING THAT MAPU [UNITED POPULAR ACTION MOVEMENT]-BARRUETO IS NOT ADDRESSING WITH THE SAME EARNESTNESS. THEY APPARENTLY SEEK TO TAKE PART IN EVERY GROUP THERE IS, WHETHER IT IS CALLED THE PPD, COSONO [SOCIALIST COMMAND FOR THE NO] OR LEFTIST PARTY.

THE CHRISTIAN LEFT PEOPLE WENT EVEN FURTHER. AT NO TIME DID THEY CONCEAL THEIR WISH THAT LUIS MAIRA PRESIDE OVER THE NEW PARTY.

THE PLENUM OF THE SOCIALIST PARTY [PS]-ALMEYDA WAS, OF COURSE, THE MOST EAGERLY ANTICIPATED. AS ON OTHER OCCASIONS, IT WAS SUPPOSED TO SET THE TONE FOR THE JOCKEYING BY THE LEFT. THEY AMBITIOUSLY FELT THAT THIS WAS THE OPPORTUNITY TO REMOVE SOME STRATEGIC OBSTACLES, SORT OF LIKE KILLING TWO BIRDS WITH ONE STONE: REGISTRATION AND THE SOUGHT-AFTER SOCIALIST UNITY.

PERHAPS THIS IS WHY THEY HELD THEIR PLENUM, WHERE ON 28 AND 29 OCTOBER THEY DISCUSSED THE ADVANTAGES OF REGISTERING THEIR OWN PARTY, IN OTHER WORDS, RESPONDING ONCE AND FOR ALL TO THE INITIATIVES OF THE NUNEZES, WHO TOOK OVER THE PPD, THE ONLY LEGALLY RECOGNIZED SOCIALIST GROUP. OTHERS THOUGHT THAT IT WOULD BE WISER TO PROMOTE A PARTY IN THE "SOCIALIST SPACE," BRING TOGETHER THERE CHRISTIAN LEFT, MAPU-BARRUETO AND THE SMALL SOCIALIST GROUPS THAT STILL EXIST, IN OTHER WORDS, COSONO AS A PARTY. THIS STAND OBVIOUSLY GAVE PRIORITY TO SOMETHING OF A LEADING POLITICAL ROLE AND KEPT THE PC AT A DISTANCE.

THE OPTION OF REGISTERING A BROAD LEFT-WING GROUP WAS ALSO RAISED AT THE PLENUM; TO MANY THIS ENTAILED A CERTAIN "SACRIFICE" OF PREDOMINANCE BY THE SOCIALISTS.

THE PS-ALMEYDA ULTIMATELY OPTED FOR A "CONSENSUS" VOTE, OF WHOSE PUBLIC VERSION THERE WERE SEVERAL INTERPRETATIONS. THERE WAS TALK OF "THE REGISTRATION OF A LEGAL INSTRUMENT REPRESENTATIVE OF THE SOCIALIST SPACE AT THE DISPOSAL OF THE GRASSROOTS FORCES AND OF THE PROGRESSIVE AND LEFTIST INDEPENDENTS WHO HAVE SO FAR BELONGED TO UNLEGALIZED PARTIES." THE INTENTION OF THE SOCIALIST LANGUAGE WAS CLEAR, BUT THE PARTY DID NOT CLOSE RANKS WITH A BROAD LEFT-WING ALLIANCE. THE EMPHASIS WAS IN THE EYE OF THE BEHOLDER.

WHAT WAS NOT MADE PUBLIC WAS THAT THE POLITICAL VOTE OF "THE MORE THAN 50 AND FEWER THAN 100 PARTICIPANTS" SPOKE OF GIVING PRIORITY TO SOCIALIST LEADERSHIP IN THE NEW PARTY. THE NEGOTIATIONS ARE NOW FOCUSING ON THIS. [CONTINUED]

TST4-MUC4-0093

BOGOTA, 14 DEC 88 (LA PRENSA) -- [COMMUNIQUE FROM THE FARC TO PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] IN THE LAST FEW DAYS OF THIS YEAR, THE NATION HAS BEEN DISCUSSING PEACE IN A WAY SELDOM HEARD OF BEFORE. ALL COLOMBIANS, INCLUDING ILLUSTRIOUS FORMER PRESIDENTS, THE MEDIA, THE CATHOLIC CHURCH, POLITICAL PARTIES, THE REBELS, AND THE NATION AT LARGE, HAVE BEEN VOICING THEIR STRONG DESIRE FOR RECONCILIATION IN THE HOMELAND.

WE REBELS HAVE ALWAYS REGARDED PEACE HIGHLY. THIS IS WHY WE HAVE ALWAYS CLEARLY REITERATED THIS IDEA. TO SET THE PROPER FRAME OF MIND, WE WILL RECALL WHAT WAS SAID IN THE LA URIBE AGREEMENT ON 28 MARCH 1984:

"TO ENSURE PEACE IN THE NATION--WHICH IS AN ESSENTIAL PREREQUISITE FOR THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE'S PROSPERITY--AND SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT BASED ON LIBERTY AND JUSTICE, THE FOLLOWING IS HEREBY AGREED UPON.

"1. THE FARC AND EP [POOR PEOPLE'S ARMY] WILL ORDER A CEASE-FIRE AND THE SUSPENSION OF ALL MILITARY OPERATIONS IN ALL FRONTS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY AS OF 0000 ON 28 MAY 1984.

"2. THE FARC AND EP WILL AGAIN CONDEMN AND NOT ALLOW KIDNAPPINGS, EXTORTION, AND TERRORISM IN ALL THEIR FORMS. FARC-EP WILL HELP ELIMINATE THESE PRACTICES BECAUSE THEY ARE AN ATTACK ON LIBERTY AND HUMAN DIGNITY."

IN ADDITION, THE M-19 AND EPL [PEOPLE'S LIBERATION ARMY] REACHED THE FOLLOWING AGREEMENT WITH THE GOVERNMENT: "... WE BELIEVE THE CESSATION OF ARMED CLASHES BETWEEN GOVERNMENT FORCES AND THE REBELS IS AN ESSENTIAL REQUIREMENT TO LAY THE GROUNDWORK FOR THE POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, AND SOCIAL REFORMS THAT THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE NEED AND DESIRE. TAKING INTO ACCOUNT THE HIGHEST INTERESTS OF THE HOMELAND, THE GOVERNMENT AND THE REBELS HAVE REACHED THE FOLLOWING AGREEMENT: THE NEGOTIATION AND DIALOGUE COMMISSION, THE EPL GENERAL COMMAND, AND THE M-19 HIGH COMMAND HAVE AGREED ON A CEASE-FIRE. ONCE THIS IS CARRIED OUT, A GREAT NATIONAL DIALOGUE WILL BEGIN, DEVELOP, AND CONCLUDE. THROUGH THIS DIALOGUE, ALL SOCIAL AND POLITICAL SECTORS WILL BE ABLE TO EXPRESS THEIR WILLINGNESS TO SEARCH FOR PEACE BASED ON SOCIAL JUSTICE.

"CONSEQUENTLY, THE EPL GENERAL COMMAND AND THE M-19 HIGH COMMAND HEREBY ORDER ALL FRONTS, COLUMNS, AND UNITS TO CEASE FIRING AND SUSPEND ALL MILITARY OPERATIONS AS OF 1300 ON 30 AUGUST."

THE SPIRIT AND THE LETTER OF THESE ACCORDS IS NOW WORTH CONSIDERING. THERE WAS A TIME WHEN COLOMBIANS SAID THESE ACCORDS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE REBELS HAD BECOME THE COUNTRY'S NEW POLITICAL PHILOSOPHY.

THIS IS NOT THE TIME FOR USELESS RECRIMINATIONS, BUT FOR A SERIOUS EFFORT TO DETERMINE WHO IS TO BLAME BECAUSE THE ACCORDS WENT PARTIALLY UNFULFILLED. ANYWAY, CONSIDERING THESE ACCORDS WILL NOT HARM THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY. WE HEREBY REAFFIRM OUR WILLINGNESS TO TALK WITH YOUR GOVERNMENT TO FIND A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE COUNTRY'S PROBLEMS. THIS WILLINGNESS TO TALK IS SHARED BY ALL OF THE MEMBERS OF THE SIMON BOLIVAR GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD AND IS PART OF THE CONCLUSIONS REACHED BY THREE GUERRILLA SUMMIT MEETINGS.

WE FULLY AGREE WITH THE PEACE PROPOSAL PRESENTED BY SENATOR ALBERTO LEYVA DURAN. WE FIND IT CLEAR, SIMPLE, UNDERSTANDABLE, AND COMPLETE. THIS IS WHY WE WROTE THIS LETTER, MADE OUR LATEST STATEMENTS, AND HAVE GIVEN INSTRUCTIONS FOR A UNILATERAL CEASE-FIRE AS THE BEST CHRISTMAS GIFT FOR OUR PEOPLE.

[SIGNED] MANUEL MARULANDA VELEZ, JACOBO ARENAS, ALFONSO CANO, RAUL REYES, TIMOLEON JIMENEZ

FARC GENERAL STAFF, SIMON BOLIVAR GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD

TST4-MUC4-0094

LIMA, 20 DEC 88 (EFE) -- [REPORT] [FRANCISCO FIGUEROA] [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN GOVERNING PARTY, APRA, TODAY ENDED A CONFLICTIVE PARTY CONGRESS ON A NOTE OF DEFEAT FOR PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA, AND WITH THE EMERGENCE OF FORMER PRIME MINISTER LUIS ALVA CASTRO AS NEW PARTY LEADER.

THE APRA CONGRESS ELIMINATED THE POST OF PARTY PRESIDENT, WHICH WAS CREATED FOR ALAN GARCIA IN 1985, CONSOLIDATING HIS POSITION AS PARTY LEADER FOLLOWING A DECISIVE VICTORY IN THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF THAT YEAR.

ACCORDING TO SOME CRITICS WITHIN THE PARTY, THE PERSONALISM THAT HAD CHARACTERIZED GARCIA'S UNDISPUTED LEADERSHIP SINCE 1982 WAS THUS ENDED.

LUIS ALVA CASTRO, 46, FORMER PRIME MINISTER AND ECONOMY MINISTER AS WELL AS FORMER PRESIDENT OF THE CHAMBER OF DEPUTIES, WAS ELECTED BY A LARGE MARGIN AS THE NEW SECRETARY GENERAL, A POST WHICH REGAINED THE HIGHEST STATUS IN THE PARTY. ALVA CASTRO CAPITALIZED ON THE INTERNAL DISSIDENCE AND ON THE PARTY'S DISENCHANTMENT WITH ALAN GARCIA AS A RESULT OF THE DETERIORATION OF THE SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC SITUATION, WHICH IS CONSIDERED THE WORST CRISIS IN THIS CENTURY AND IS BLAMED ON THE CHIEF OF STATE'S "STUBBORNNESS" IN NOT CHANGING HIS NATIONALISTIC AND POPULIST POLICY LINE."

THE NEW CADRE ELECTED AT THE 16TH APRA CONGRESS IS IN FAVOR OF A "CHANGE IN ORIENTATION" IN THE PARTY'S MANAGEMENT AND IN THE PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION FOR THE REMAINING 18 MONTHS OF THE APRA'S TERM IN OFFICE. IT IS EXPECTED THAT ALAN GARCIA AND ALVA CASTRO MAY REACH AN AGREEMENT ON THE WAY THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE RUN UNTIL 1990, WHEN THE CURRENT PRESIDENTIAL TERM WILL END FOLLOWING NEW GENERAL ELECTIONS.

GARCIA ALSO LOST THE PRESIDENCY OF THE POLITICAL COMMISSION THAT SETS THE PARTY'S POLITICAL LINE. THIS POST WAS WON BY LUIS ALBERTO SANCHEZ, 88, FIRST VICE PRESIDENT OF THE NATION AND ONE OF THE MAINSPRINGS IN THE CHANGEOVER OPERATION WITHIN THE APRA.

THE OTHER ELECTIVE POSITIONS WERE FILLED WITH APRA MEMBERS WHO DO NOT FOLLOW GARCIA'S LINE. THUS, THE PRESENCE OF ALAN GARCIA WITHIN THE PARTY WAS REDUCED TO BEING MEMBER OF THE POLITICAL COMMISSION IN HIS CAPACITY AS FORMER PARTY SECRETARY GENERAL.

TWO DAYS AGO, THE PERUVIAN CHIEF OF STATE RESIGNED THE APRA PRESIDENCY, UPSET OVER CRITICISM DIRECTED AT HIM DURING THE OPENING OF THE PARTY CONGRESS. HE THUS RESPONDED TO OBVIOUS SIGNS THAT THE PARTY PRESIDENT POST WOULD BE ELIMINATED.

THE APRA HAD THOUGHT ALAN GARCIA WOULD BE A VERY CAPABLE HEIR TO VICTOR RAUL HAYA DE LA TORRE, THE PARTY'S FOUNDER AND HISTORICAL LEADER, WHO DIED IN 1979. THREE AND ONE-HALF YEARS AFTER GARCIA'S ELECTION VICTORY, THE PARTY DISQUALIFIED GARCIA FOR THE ROLE OF HAYA DE LA TORRE'S SUCCESSOR BECAUSE OF HIS ERRORS AND HIS FAILURE TO RECTIFY HIS GOVERNMENT LINE.

FOLLOWING THE TRADITION INITIATED BY ALAN GARCIA, NEW APRA LEADER LUIS ALVA CASTRO WILL BE SWORN IN AS SECRETARY GENERAL THIS COMING FRIDAY BEFORE THE TOMB OF HAYA DE LA TORRE IN THE NORTHERN CITY OF TRUJILLO, THE APRA'S MAIN BASTION.

THE ECONOMIC CRISIS, MARKED BY 2,000-PERCENT INFLATION AND A 20-PERCENT RECESSION FROM OCTOBER 1987 TO OCTOBER 1988, IS COMPOUNDED BY SOCIAL INSTABILITY AND POLITICAL VIOLENCE, WITH KILLINGS AVERAGING FOUR PER DAY.

AN INTERNAL POLITICAL STORM HIT THE APRA 16TH NATIONAL CONGRESS, AND VICE PRESIDENT SANCHEZ SAID THAT HE CANNOT RECALL ANYTHING SIMILAR.

DURING THE LAST SESSION OF THE CONGRESS, THREE YOUTHS WERE INJURED IN A MELEE AMONG APRA PEOPLE. OTHER PARTY MEMBERS WERE HIT ON THE HEAD WITH HANDGUN BUTTS, AND THREE NEWSMEN--WHO HAD NOT BEEN ALLOWED TO ATTEND THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE CONGRESS--WERE ATTACKED.

TST4-MUC4-0096

RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL), 22 DEC 88 (REDE GLOBO TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] SAO PAULO FEDERAL POLICE HAVE SEIZED TWO DRUG TRAFFICKERS CARRYING 160 KILOGRAMS OF COCAINE. THIS IS THE LARGEST DRUG SEIZURE THIS YEAR IN SAO PAULO.

AT 2130 IN THE LOCAL NEIGHBORHOOD OF PLATINEDI, A CAR PASSING 2 BLOCKS FROM THE PUBLIC SECURITY SECRETARY OF THE STATE WAS SURROUNDED BY A GROUP OF FEDERAL POLICEMEN ARMED WITH PISTOLS AND MACHINEGUNS. IN A QUICK OPERATION, A MAN AND A WOMAN WERE ARRESTED AND THE CAR WAS TAKEN TO THE DISTRICT POLICE OFFICE. ONLY TODAY WERE THE CONTENTS OF THE CAR EXHIBITED: SEVEN SUITCASES WITH 51 PLASTIC BAGS CONTAINING A TOTAL OF 160 KILOGRAMS OF COCAINE. THIS AMOUNT OF COCAINE IS WORTH NEARLY $2 MILLION. TO DISGUISE THE ODOR OF THE DRUG THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS PACKED SOME PINEAPPLES AMONG THE PLASTIC BAGS.

THE FEDERAL POLICE DID NOT REVEAL THE DETAILS OF THE OPERATION, NOR DID THEY IDENTIFY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS. IT WAS LEARNED THAT THEY ARE LEOPOLDO GOMES PORTAO AND GENILDE FERNANDES MORAIS, WHO LIVE IN CORUMBA, MATO GROSSO DO SUL. THEY PICKED UP THE COCAINE IN BOLIVIA, AND THEY WERE GOING TO DISTRIBUTE IT IN SAO PAULO AND RIO DE JANEIRO.

THE FEDERAL POLICE REVEALED THAT LEOPOLDO GOMES PORTAO HAD ALREADY SERVED PRISON TIME TWICE FOR DRUG TRAFFICKING, AND THAT THE CAR HE WAS DRIVING HAD BEEN STOLEN IN RIO DE JANEIRO.

TST4-MUC4-0098

SAN SALVADOR, 22 DEC 88 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] NATIONAL POLICE DIRECTOR COLONEL CARLOS MAURICIO GUZMAN AGUILAR ANNOUNCED TODAY THAT EIGHT GUERRILLAS, MEMBERS OF THE FMLN URBAN COMMAND UNITS, ARE BEING HELD BY THE NATIONAL POLICE. FOUR OF THE GUERRILLAS WERE CAPTURED IN THE MALAGA NEIGHBORHOOD TUESDAY FOLLOWING A SHOOT-OUT WITH POLICE.

GUZMAN AGUILAR DISCLOSED THAT ONE OF THE EIGHT GUERRILLAS IS THE DAUGHTER OF A UNIVERSITY LEADER. THE EIGHT REBELS WERE CAPTURED DURING THE PAST 48 HOURS AND CHARGED WITH BEING MEMBERS OF THE FMLN URBAN COMMAND UNITS. THE FIRST FOUR SUSPECTED GUERRILLAS WERE DETAINED AFTER THEY ATTACKED TWO POLICEMEN AND CRASHED THE VEHICLE THEY WERE IN. THE POLICE SEIZED LARGE-CALIBER WEAPONS FROM THEM.

LATER, DURING THE POLICE INVESTIGATION, THE FOUR REBELS SUPPLIED INFORMATION TO LOCATE ANOTHER URBAN GUERRILLA GROUP, THE POLICE DIRECTOR NOTED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GUZMAN AGUILAR] THE NATIONAL POLICE CAPTURED FOUR INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE MEMBERS OF URBAN COMMAND UNITS. THEIR NAMES ARE: CARLOS ELIAS MENJIVAR GUEVARA, RENE ARMANDO GUEVARA MARTINEZ, MARCO TULIO MOLINA ESCOBAR, AND CLAUDIA INES CANJURA GUILLEN. CANJURA GUILLEN IS THE DAUGHTER OF CARLOS CANJURA, WHO IS THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNIVERSITY'S GENERAL ASSEMBLY.

YESTERDAY, CANJURA AND THE UNIVERSITY LAWYER WENT TO THE POLICE STATION TO ASK ABOUT HIS DAUGHTER'S WHEREABOUTS. ACCORDING TO HIM, SHE HAD DISAPPEARED 2 OR 3 DAYS AGO AND HE HAD FOUND OUT THAT THE POLICE WERE HOLDING HER.

BASED ON INFORMATION SUPPLIED BY THE ARRESTED GUERRILLAS, THE POLICE ARRESTED ANOTHER FOUR INDIVIDUALS YESTERDAY IN THE ZACAMILLO NEIGHBORHOOD. THEY ARE: JAIME ALEXANDER ATENCIO VALLADARES, LUIS SAN SALVADOR RIVAS CARRILLO, ANA RUTH MERINO DIAZ, AND CLAUDIA CAROLINA SANCHEZ FLORES.

FOLLOWING THE SHOOT-OUT BETWEEN THE POLICE AND REBELS IN MONSERRAT [NAME AS HEARD], POLICE FOUND AND SEIZED THE FOLLOWING WEAPONS IN THE GUERRILLAS' CAR: TWO ROMANIAN MP-24 9-MM SUBMACHINEGUNS, ONE NORTH KOREAN 9-MM PISTOL, ONE .38 CALIBER HUNGARIAN-MADE PISTOL, 4 HAND GRENADES, AND 4 STICKS OF TNT. [END RECORDING]

GUZMAN AGUILAR SAID THAT AFTER THE 72 HOURS THAT THE LAW ALLOWS TO PROCESS AN INMATE PASS, THE EIGHT GUERRILLAS WILL BE TURNED OVER TO JUDICIAL AUTHORITIES, WHO WILL DETERMINE THE INMATES' RESPONSIBLITY FOR THESE ACTS.

THE MILITARY OFFICER MADE THESE STATEMENTS AT THE PUBLIC SECURITY MILITARY ACADEMY DURING A CEREMONY TO SWEAR IN 19 NEW NATIONAL POLICE OFFICERS.